<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The triumphant lady: or, The crowned innocence· A choice and authentick piece of the famous, De Ceriziers, almoner to the King. / Translated into English, out of the original French, by Sir William Lower Knight.</title>
            <title>Histoire d'Hirlande, ou l'Innocence couronnée. English</title>
            <author>Cerisiers, René de, 1609-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1682</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1617_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209636</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868501</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868501</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170162</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78453)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170162)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 204:E1617[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The triumphant lady: or, The crowned innocence· A choice and authentick piece of the famous, De Ceriziers, almoner to the King. / Translated into English, out of the original French, by Sir William Lower Knight.</title>
                  <title>Histoire d'Hirlande, ou l'Innocence couronnée. English</title>
                  <author>Cerisiers, René de, 1609-1662.</author>
                  <author>Lower, William, Sir, 1600?-1662.</author>
                  <author>Gaywood, Richard, fl. 1650-1680, engraver.</author>
                  <author>Barlow, Francis, 1626?-1702, artist.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 142 p. : ill. (metal cut);  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ga. Bedell, and Tho. Collins, and are to be sold at their shop at the Middle-Temple Gate in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Cerisiers, René de.  L'Histoire d'Hirlande, ou l'Innocence couronnée.</note>
                  <note>The engraved frontispiece is signed by R. Gaywood after F[rancis] B[arlow], 1655.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "February 29"; the 6 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a 5.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170162:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Triumphant Lady:</hi> OR, The CROWNED INNOCENCE.</p>
            <p>A Choice and Authentick Piece of the Famous, <hi>DeCERIZIERS,</hi> Almoner to the King.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated into ENGLISH, out of the Original FRENCH, BY Sir <hi>WILLIAM LOWER</hi> KNIGHT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for GA. BEDELL, and THO. COLLINS, and are to be ſold at their Shop at the Middle-Temple Gate in Fleet-ſtreet, 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:170162:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170162:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170162:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170162:3"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I touch upon the Lady, who is now to be the glorious Subject of my Diſcourſe, give me leave, I pray you, to look back a little upon my <hi>Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Innocence, Genivieva,</hi> whom I am obliged to vindicate. Me thinks I hear ſome ignorant Incredulous ſay, that ſhe is a Romantick Lady, a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous Divinity, and no Authentick Piece, as I have ſet her forth in my Prefaces to the world. To convince their Errour, to clear their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and to rectifie their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I would have them know, that I drew it forth juſt ſo as it is to be ſeen with <hi>Puteanus,</hi> and <hi>Raderus</hi> in his <hi>Bavaria. Aubert Miréus</hi> having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in his Belgick Feaſts many prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:170162:4"/>to that holy Princeſs, aſſureth that her Life is written by <hi>Matthew Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> of the Order of the Reverend Fathers <hi>Carmilites,</hi> or <hi>White Friers,</hi> and which is conſerved yet to this day in the Charter houſe of <hi>Conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> upon the <hi>Rhine.</hi> Now though I might ſay, that all that which I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of that generous Woman is true, ſince it might arrive unto her indeed, and that the fair Apparitions which I deſcribed, were ſhewed to her ſpirit, yet I will content you, and diſcover with ſimplicity what is purely of her Hiſtory. It is true, that <hi>Genevieva</hi> Princeſs of the Houſe of <hi>Brabant,</hi> was married to a Palatine of <hi>Treues;</hi> it is true, that ſhe ſwouned at the departure of her <hi>Sifroy;</hi> that ſhe was fair, and tempted by <hi>Golo:</hi> it is true, that ſhe gave him a box, and that he put her into Priſon; that her husband commanded her death upon a ſuſpition which this evil ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant gave him, through the Artifices of a woman, ſuſpected of Magick. It
<pb facs="tcp:170162:4"/>is true, that two of his Domeſticks upon the point of killing her, left her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; and that they met a little dog, which loſt his tongue to conſerve that of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs. It is true, that a voice promiſed her the aſſiſtance of heaven, entring into the wood, and that a Hind nouriſhed her child the ſpace of ſeven years. It is true that the Palatine in Hunting, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted into his Wives Cave, and that he knew her. It is true, that he made her Slanderer to dye with the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which I obſerved, that that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Lady ended holily, after ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Communion, that they built an Hermitage in the place of her Penitence, and that we have ſeen there in the following ages our Lady of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen.</hi> If I ſaid that her Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fie ſpake to her, it is to be interpreted of that mute language, wherewith God ſpeaks inwardly to his Favourites, or we ſhould remember <hi>Peter the Martyr.</hi> When the Croſſe followed her, that was meant ſpiritually, as it happens to all the afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or really, as to the moſt Bleſſed <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel
<pb facs="tcp:170162:5"/>d'Vuans.</hi> The Wolf which cloathed the little <hi>Benoni,</hi> could he not uſe the ſame gratitude with the <hi>Hyena</hi> of the great <hi>Macaires.</hi> It would be eaſie for me to find all the other circumſtances of my <hi>Illuſtrious Innocence,</hi> if it were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way neceſſary; but I think it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make confeſſ'd, that I gave no Fictions to thoſe that took the pains to read it. In my opinion, this illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration ſufficeth to undeceive thoſe who think to be deceived. It only reſts unto me to anſwer thoſe Sages who wonder at this, that <hi>Genevieva</hi> remained ſo long unknown, and who demand if it were not eaſie for her to retire to her patents. Certainly, theſe Demands ſhould be made to <hi>Genevieva</hi> rather then to me; notwithſtading I think that one ſhould not doubt of a Hiſtory, as ſoon as one meets there ſome circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances difficult to receive. If God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted that this Vertuous Princeſſe ſhould be miſtaken by her owne huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, is there any cauſe of Admiration that no body hath knowne her? Was
<pb facs="tcp:170162:5"/>there not more cauſe to wonder at this, that his Providence having given us his Son for three years, he hid him thirty years in a Country the moſt frequented of the earth, and in the moſt famous Town of the Univerſe? God hides himſelfe in the midſt of the Sun, why could he not hide a woman in an infinite Forreſt, and in Dens which make wild Beaſts afraid? His Providence labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſelf to turne aſide thoſe, whom ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard or deſigne would conduct unto that ſolitude, to trouble the devotions of our Saint. When God ſpeaks in ſecret unto any one, he draws him aſide: but as his Diſcourſes are important, they are commonly long. And why ſhould God have inſpired the thought of <hi>Genevieva</hi> to retire her ſelf toward her Parents, who might be dead or ill affectionated? Moreover, my Reader, Heaven would not revenge an Innocent, it pretended only to ſee a Saint to ſuffer. The Court of Princes, where there is nothing but delights, was not proper for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. I care not to ſatisfie thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:170162:6"/>complain of the reaſon and reſentments which I gave to the Animals and to the Trees, upon the miſeries and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of <hi>Genevieva.</hi> This reproach comes (without doubt) but from thoſe who know not the Liberty of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratour; who may even in the judgment of the moſt ſevere Maſters, make the plants and ſtones to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>So much for <hi>Genevieva.</hi> For <hi>Hirlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> whoſe Triumphant life I now treat of; I ſuppoſe I ſhall need no Apology, becauſe none will deny her the Crown, but ſuch as are ſtupid or malicious: yet I foreſee that thoſe who will have demonſtrations of Mathematicks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the truth of Hiſtory, will not fail to quarrel with her whom I ſerve, and that ſome people will take it for a tale made for paſtime.</p>
            <p>My Reader, before you take part with the Incredulous, or Eaſie, I pray you to remember; that you believe more ſtrange ones upon the recital of <hi>Titus Livius,</hi> and <hi>Quintus Curtius,</hi> and that there are many ſuch in our beſt
<pb facs="tcp:170162:6"/>Books. And then though this ſhould be a ſymbolick Hiſtory, ſhould I not be pardoned this Liberty in this kind of Writings: ſince it is granted, that Saint <hi>John Damaſcene</hi> hath uſed them in the Life of his <hi>Joſaphat.</hi> It would be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie for me to imploy the example of the Queen <hi>Elvira,</hi> or of the Empreſs <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda,</hi> which I have touched in my fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe, but beſides that their adventures have circumſtances as ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected as thoſe which I propoſe, they are too common not to be known.</p>
            <p>Receive then my <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> whom I have drawn by the cares of one of our Fathers worthy of credit, from a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript of the Town of <hi>Autun.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps without his Diligence and Charity ſhe might remain forever buried in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion. We know, thanks be to God, what can be objected to this Hiſtory; but we know wel alſo what ought to be anſwered thereunto. If I would wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, I ſhould find without trouble as much probability for me recital, as the Objectors pretend to give prop to their
<pb facs="tcp:170162:7"/>doubt. I force no body to receive my ſentiments; if any one will be obſtinate, let him permit me to be plain. In caſe that I deceive my ſelf, my errour ſhall not be of thoſe whereof Hereſies are made; and likewiſe I dare to aſſure it leſſe criminal then a preſumptious knowledg; ſince that ſimplicity which hath no malice ought not to ſuffer any reproach. Remember notwithſtanding, that though I ſay that <hi>Hirlanda</hi> was Dutcheſſe of <hi>Bretany,</hi> this ought to be underſtood according to the <hi>Alamans</hi> manner of ſpeaking, who call all the Princes of a Houſe, Duke or Marqueſs of the Province whereof it beares the name. For example, in their uſe, thoſe of <hi>Saxony,</hi> of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> or of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> take the title thereof, though they poſſeſs not the demain. And ſurely it is not to divine in my own cauſe, ſince <hi>Dargentreius</hi> and other Authors of the Hiſtory of <hi>Bretanie,</hi> ſpeak often enough in this manner. You will judg wel that the ornaments which I give it, ſet it forth without altering it, and that by this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct
<pb facs="tcp:170162:7"/>I indeavour to inſtruct and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the ſpirit, without pretending to corrupt it.</p>
            <p>Would to God that thoſe pens which are held up to be delicate, would imploy themſelves to collect in the ſame deſign the diverſe accidents of Hiſtory, without amuſing them in making worlds fairer then that which God hath made. We ſhould ſee that our youth would become learned in recreating themſelves, and that thoſe fatal ſources which empoiſon ſo many ſouls, would be dry by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per induſtry of thoſe that have given them courſe. Whilſt that theſe fair wits ſhall reſolve themſelves to render this good ſervice to the Church, I conjure thoſe that ſhall do me the honour to read this work, to read it with equity &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pre-occupation; perhaps they will find here no leſs divertiſement &amp; profit, then there is danger in thoſe myſterious pieces. Let us not leave our ſelvs to be deceived by that ridiculous perſwaſion which the divel upholds with all his power, that fair expreſſions belong not
<pb facs="tcp:170162:8"/>but to the family of <hi>Theagines</hi> and <hi>Chari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lea.</hi> Why ſhould the language of the Religious be as rude as their robe and their life? Make they profeſſion of ill ſpeaking, or rather, come they all from <hi>Arabia,</hi> or from ſome country more ſavage? Have we not ſeen ſome of them who were clothed with the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pomp of the world, to ſeek under this vertuous diſguiſement the ſouls: which run to their ruine? What wil they? that Love; who is but a child, ſhould render men eloquent; and that Zeal, which is a Seraphin, ſhould not hinder them to be mute? Let us grant notwithſtanding, that there is as little ill inſtruction in the works of thoſe Meſſieurs, as choice words in ours; who ſhould dare to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that there is merit to read them? But if we derive no advantage from this reading, and that all the ſages aſſure that it is not without ſuſpition of crime, who will be ſo prodigal of his time, as to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon himſelf to this dangerous idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? All poſterity mocketh that Biſhop, who would rather loſe his Miter, then
<pb facs="tcp:170162:8"/>diſavow a fable. Permit me to tel you, my reader, that one would make a much worſe judgment of your obſtination, if not to quit for a teſtoon of paper, you ſhould imprudently hazard Paradiſe. But one learns the world and civility from Romance; grant that it be ſo: who will reſolve himſelf to loſe inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, or at leaſt to hazard it upon the expectation of ſo ſmall a gain? I aſſure not that, which notwithſtanding is but too true, that the reading of theſe pieces is much more fatal to good manners, then that of thoſe other works which openly make profeſſion to inſtruct men in debauchery. Every one can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it by this ſole reflection, that we have horrour of a declared enemy, and uſe precaution againſt the danger which is known unto us. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, there is no perſon that helps not to deceive himſelf, when the occaſion of failing ſeems to favour the inclination which it intends to corrupt. To ſpeak truth, I know not who will give his approbation to Romances, after the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb facs="tcp:170162:9"/>
               <hi>Francis de Sales</hi> hath ſtrucken them with <hi>Anathema.</hi> I will not make uſe of the anſwer which he made to a Lady who conſulted him upon that kind of writings: it ſufficeth me to let you know, that this great Prelate named them the Prentiſhip of a trade which is infamous enough. Would it pleaſed God, for the little love which I have, for me, and the perfect hate which I bear to thoſe agreeable corrupters of innocence, that their work and mine were reduced into aſhes to choak that blood-ſucker. But ſince that all my tears, and thoſe of good people deface not one of their lines, I will never ceaſe to continue the endeavour which I uſe to procure their ruine: perhaps though my weakneſs gives ſubject unto ſome to laugh, it will inſpire courage and will in others to ſuccour me.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:170162:9"/>
            <head>DISCOURSE. That it is a greater and more noble Effect of Courage to ſuffer then to revenge Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ORCE, a Principal and moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Vertue of man hath two Effects, Sufferance and Action: and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs me more neatly; Force acteth with Courage, and ſuſtaineth with Patience. By its firſt Office it ſhould moderate that generous impetuoſity, which ſolicites us continually unto great Enterpriſes; and by the ſecond, it repreſſeth the fears which the diſtruſt of our power imprinteth in us at the encounter of the difficult. <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> the cleareſt of all thoſe who have known Nature, aſſureth in the third Book of his Morals, that the Force which ſuſtaines meriteth much more praiſe, then that which aſſaulteth: Behold his reaſons, There is this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between him that acteth, and him that ſuffereth, that the firſt is the maſter of his Action, and therefore as the beginning of his endeavour is in his liberty, his progreſſe depends of his conſtancy. If he knows him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf weak, he ceaſeth; nothing obligeth him to carry on his aſſault but the hope of the Victory which he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun. On the contrary, the ſecond is conſtrained in the ſufferance, for as much as the relief of his evil ſprings from the ſole defect of power in thoſe that labour him. Now who ſees not that it is more difficult to remain long immoveable in the Conflict of grief (that which Patience ought to do) then to be moved with reſolution for ſome moments to the deſigne of great things, which proceedeth from courage? from whence I conclude,
<pb facs="tcp:170162:10"/>ſince it is more eafie to have vigour for ſome minutes, then for months and yeers it is leſſe in our power to be patient then couragious. Moreover, he that ſuffers, hath all his evil preſent, and he that aſſaults ſees his only to come: yea the evil of the Patient, is a grief real which torments him, and that of the Couragious is oftentimes but an imagination which threatens him. I think no body doubts that the preſent grief is not more incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious, then that which we look upon in the future. Nature is moved in the apprehenſion of the evil which ſhewes it ſelf, but ſhe deſpaires in the combat of that which afflicts her; nothing comforts her in the actual convulſions of her pain, and a thouſand precautions promiſe her ſuccour, when her miſery is diſtant. That great Philoſopher of whom I borrow theſe Reaſons, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth a third better then the others. Never doth the Courage reſolve it ſelf to the purſuit of an enemy, but it promiſeth it ſelf the Victory: On the contrary, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience ſcarce ſees her ſelf aſſailed, but ſhe apprchends to be overcome. It is not a diſcretion that we ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from an Adverſary to accommodate himſelf to our forces, in ſuch manner as be would diſpute with us the advantage with honour. As his deſign is to vanquiſh, his wiſdom is to meaſure himſelf before the Combat; if he ſees himſelf not able, he careth not to hazard himſelf; but if he thinks that he hath more ſtrength then his enemy hath reſiſtance then he contracts himſelf, drawing new forces from the weakneſſe of another. Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> upholds the ſentiments of <hi>Ariſtorle</hi> with this ſolid Diſcourſe. One cannot doubt that the perfect ſuppreſſion of fear is not more hard to find, then the juſt temperament of choler which are the two effects of Force; then there is more mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in ſufferance then in action. For as much as danger which is the proper ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of choler and fear, concurs of it ſelf, and by its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural condition to moderate audaci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it aideth timility. And therefore the repreſſion of
<pb facs="tcp:170162:10"/>fear is leſſe eaſie then the moderation of the motion, which is oppoſed to it: for beſides th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t our inclination is for Choler, which accompanies courage; patience is alwayes followed of fear, which is, the ſtrong eſt to be the weakeſt of our affections. Now it is certain, that it belongeth to Force to aſſault, for as much as it rules audacitie, and ſuſtaines in correcting fear. It is leſſe then, to do, then to ſuffer. So the Holy Ghoſt praiſing the Beauties of his Spouſe, ſpeaks not of her armed hand, but of her neck adorned with a thouſand Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, becauſe we have a thouſand evils from which we ſhould defend our ſelves. From all this Diſpute I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, That there is much more Courage to ſuffer Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny, then to revenge it, ſince Revenge acteth, and Patience ſuſtaineth. Though this truth remaines ſtrongly enough eſtabliſhed upon theſe Reaſons, I think it fit to add ſome others, which are proper to the ſubject which I treat of. It is not a little glory to triumph of an enemy, whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate is no leſſe unjuſt then damagea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; for as much as he who is the Conqueror of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſeemes to become the Maſter. So that the ſame Motive which thruſts us on to ſuperiority, ſolicites us to revenge. But we ought to obſerve, that man having more averſion from Infamy then love for eſteem, it is more glorious to repreſſe the ſentiments of injury, then to ſatisfie the appetite of glory. The ſecret principle of this inclination is found in that reaſonable intereſt, which per ſwades us, that the entire ruine of our being excites more our fears and flights, then its perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on merits our deſires and ſearcher. So is it certaine, (what greedineſſe ſoever we have for reputation) that we never hazard its purſuit in the occaſions of diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. A great Courage gives it ſelf up unto the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of loſing life, becauſe he ſees his recompence in the eſteem; but he with-holds himſelf from the Encounter of reproach, becauſe he feareth the Infamy. Therefore it is no wonder if I ſay, that it is more to ſuffer detraction
<pb facs="tcp:170162:11"/>which indeavours to ſully us, then to revenge it, fince the peaceable acquieſment hath this ill witneſſe, that we love ignominy, and the effort which we make to reject it diſcovereth our impatience. And really, to conſider the forces which we imploy in the one and the other, we ſhall find that reaſon alone aids us to ſuffer Calumny, and that a great number of paſſions thruſt us on to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge it. We have alwayes eſteemed a Victory by the little aſſiſtance of the Conqueror, and by the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Conquered. Who can then deny, that a man who combats with Reaſon alone againſt a great crowd of enemies, meriteth no more Elogies, then he who is ſucoured of all ſides? All the difficulty that there is to ſuffer comes not from the infirmity of the perſon that ſuffers, it comes alſo from the power of the cauſes, which produce the ſufferance. Add unto that, that very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten there is no hope to acquire glory; and that one hath alwayes cauſe to require the ſatisfaction thereof by Juſtice. But if the difficulty of a work augments the glory and price thereof, it is not hard to conclude of that which I have ſaid, that the Couragious who repulſeth the outrage, meriteth leſſe Praiſe and Recompence, then the patient that endures it. So muſt it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that the laſt proof of Chriſtian generoſity is in the pardon of the Offence, ſince it is more eaſie to give our goods then our reſentments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We may permit without crying, that force take our Wealth from us, for they are not tyed to our fleſh; but we cannot ſuffer without patience, that one ſhould raviſh Glory from us, becauſe it is glued to our ſpirit. Much more it ſeems eaſie to witneſſe Conſtancy, when one cuts off a member from us, which hath no annection but with a part of our body, then to uſe reſignation when one loſeth ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, which relateth to the whole ſoul. This Diſcourſe makes it ſufficiently to be comprehended, that Patience i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> myſtery of Chriſtianity, and that at leſſe then the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of a God, we could not have known a Vertue,
<pb facs="tcp:170162:11"/>which makes us enemies of our ſelvs. But if the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity which we practiſe in ſuffering, meriteth glory, what praiſe ſhould we not give to the courage of thoſe who loſe without diſpleaſure what all men ſeek with ſo much zeal? It belongs not but unto Jeſus Chriſt, and unto thoſe that are neer his Croſſe, to bear peaceably the outrages which it is juſt and glorious to repulſe. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can reſolve us thereunto, but the example and grace of a God, ſince Nature is repugnant unto it, and reaſon forbids not to purſue the puniſhment thereof.</p>
            <p>But to put this truth into a light which may be ſeen and ſenſible to all the world, I think it fit to joyn Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to reaſon. That which I will produce, carries an illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious proof of the courage which revengeth the calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and of the patience that ſuffers it. Since all the evil comes from the ſide where the North wind bloweth (to ſpeak in the terms of the Holy Ghoſt) it is not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to draw from thence ſome famous example of ſlander. <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> having reſolved to chuſe a Princeſs that might partake with him the delights of his Empire, he fixed his thought upon one of the daughters of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>England.</hi> Though he had never ſeen <hi>Matilda,</hi> her portrait gave him love; ſo muſt he confeſs that the pencil never did better in the expreſſion of all the parts, which make up a perfect viſage. But what! if the copy of an excellent beauty could kindle ſo many inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent fires; is there not cauſe to fear that its Original made fatal combuſtions? Love is a flame of another nature then that of the lightning, which fixeth but on the oaks and firre; ſhe ſpareth not the meaneſt fortunes, becauſe very often their ambition as wel as their deſign is to burn; contrary to thoſe humble plants that hide themſelves in the fire of heaven, for fear to be percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of it. Behold the misfortune that happened, (as the Hiſtory relates it) to a Gentleman of the Emperours houſe. This raſh perſon having beheld his Miſtreſs
<pb facs="tcp:170162:12"/>with too much curiouſity, had ſo little diſcretion as to speak of Love to a Queen, who peſſeſſed as much ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue as ſhe had beauty. The refuſal which he received, gave him with the ſhame of his demand, a lively appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the puniſhment which his preſumption meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. To divert the ſtorm thereof, he judged that he muſt gain the ſpirit of <hi>Henry,</hi> and prevent his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the complaint which he believed <hi>Matilda</hi> would make unto him of his impudence: In this deſign he ſpake to the Emperour, and told him with much candour, that his wife ceaſed not to ſolicite him to a diſloyalty, the ſole thought whereof, he ſuppoſed would be culpable. In a word, that the Princeſs would have him for her friend. Wee have ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en but very few So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns that take pleaſure to divide their Crown; but we ſee yet fewer husbands that ſuffer the participation of their bed. The woman is a Kingdom of the man; (as St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> aſſures it) if this Monarchy degenerates into a Republick, the Monarch falls into fury: perhaps <hi>Henry</hi> would have diſſembled if any one of his Provinces had given it ſelf to a tyrant, but his indignation witneſſed well that be could not ſuffer that his wife ſhould offer her ſelf to one of his ſervants. The ſuſpition that he received of her upon the report of a ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, cauſed that he caſt <hi>Matilda</hi> into priſon, ſwearing by his Scepter and his Life, that the blood of that unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Princeſs ſhould waſh off that ſpot, if no body pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented himſelf for the proof of her innocence. Behold then that poor Queen in a ſtrait priſon, where the horror of death could not make her to pronounce one word of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair or of murmur: ſhe adored the Providence that permitted her oppreſſion; but if ſhe spake or deplored, it was but to witneſs the joy of her ſufferance. That ſhee might not betray her vertue, ſhe was contented to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt once of her innocence, and to ſay, that never ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her body or her heart were divided. They ſay, that jealoufie is an exceſs of love, and that a husband
<pb facs="tcp:170162:12"/>would never fear to loſe the affection of his wife, if he eſteem'd her not much, and judged her not worthy to be ſought. Let every one believe hereof what be will, for my part. I maintain that this diſtruſtful paſſion takes more from hatred, then from love, ſince it looks but upon the ruine of its object in ſtead of procuring the advantages of it. Never will any one think that <hi>Henry</hi> loved <hi>Matilda</hi> with exceſs, if he conſiders that he perſecuted her without pity; all things were dispoſed for the puniſhment of this deplorable Princeſs, and they began already to dreſs her a wood pile, according to the cuſtom then<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which was that an adulterous woman ſhould expire in the flames: the lamentable spectacle of this ſad preparation could not change the countenance of the Princeſs; to ſee her conſtancy, one would judg that it was a Comedy, in which every one acted well his part, except ſhe who was the ſubject thereof. As they expected the day which was to ſhut the lifts to the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions of the Empreſs; there arrived a Hermit at the Court who was permitted entrance into the priſon from whence <hi>Matilda</hi> beheld death to come. This Religious man, after he had heard the general confeſſion of the poor Queen, and known her perfect innocence, departed out of the priſon to appear the next day in the liſts, with reſolution to defend a vertue which he ſaw unjuſtly oppreſſed. I will not extend the ceremonies of this combat, it is ſufficient to ſay, that heaven ayded for this bout the good intention of a ſimple in behalf of an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. The Calumniator was conſtrained to confeſs the vertue of <hi>Matilda,</hi> and afterward to die upon an infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Gibbet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I know that this History hath nothing good but its end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that there is nothing but the cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the former ages that can justifie it. That Cavalier which preſented himſelf for Champion to the Princeſs, was quite otherwiſe then he ſeem'd to be; the habit of a Religious man under which he appeared, ſerved as a vail to his deſign, and not as veſtment to his profeſſion:
<pb facs="tcp:170162:13"/>and not to diſguiſe a diſguiſement, it was a French Prince, who touch'd with the miſery of <hi>Matilda,</hi> had quitted his Court to come to defend Innocence, after he had known by the artifice which he uſed, the truth or falſhood of her accuſation. As he had finiſhed an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe which would be glorious in all its circumſtances, if it had not imployed that unlawful means, he retired him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, remaining unknown, as before. If the Hiſtory aſſured us not that it was the laſt of the <hi>Berangers,</hi> Count of <hi>Barcelona</hi> and <hi>Provence,</hi> whom it names different from the others, <hi>Remond Teſte d'eſtoupe,</hi> we ſhould not know yet his name and quality. Thoſe who have thought that the merit of that protection acquired him <hi>Provence,</hi> have not well read the Records, which import expreſly, that this Soveraignty came unto him by his marriage with <hi>Douce</hi> the one of its heir eſſe. All this ſuppoſed, as the Hiſtory repreſents it, I leave now to judg if <hi>Matilda</hi> meriteth not more praiſes for having ſuffered without murmur, then <hi>Remond</hi> for having vanquiſhed with good fortune. It is a ſpectacle which hath the eyes of men for witneſſes and admirers, to ſee a Prince in hazard of his life without other intereſt then of justice: but an Empreſs in infamy, and without impatience, it is in my judgment a miracle, which may arreſt both the Angels and God himſelf. The arms of <hi>Remond</hi> have aſplendor that ſhal never periſh, and the tears of <hi>Matilda</hi> a ſweetneſſe which triumphs eternally. I admire the courage of the Cavalier, but I am raviſhed with the patience of that happy unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170162:13"/>
            <head>The Triumphant Lady: OR, <hi>The Crowned Innocence.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Eares have (I know) not ſweetneſſe, which makes us to love them; and though them may be the marks of grief in thoſe that ſhed them, they are motives of joy to thoſe that conſider them. The ſole ſight of one in miſery gives the experience of this truth: But if any one remain inſenſible by an afflicted perſon, we ought to believe either that he is not a man, or rather that he is blind. The greateſt and faireſt Monſter that Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frick ever nouriſhed, confeſſeth that the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170162:14"/>agreeable Lyes of <hi>Virgil,</hi> deceived him with ſo much cunning, that he took plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to deplore with <hi>Dido,</hi> whoſe feigned griefs produced true regrets in his ſoul. But if it be true that all ſorts of Wretches draw us to the compaſſion of their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and that we reſent a kind of pleaſure to ſigh with them; it is much ſurer, when the ſubject of the affliction ſeems unto us to merit a good or leſſe rigorous fortune. That fair Offendereſſe, who ſold ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny repentances unto <hi>Greece,</hi> no ſooner ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the midſt of the <hi>Areopage,</hi> but he was changed; and thoſe that ſhould courageouſly bend their ſpirits unto Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, mollified themſelves effeminately unto love. I know that pity alone made not this ſtrange change, and that it was aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Vice, wherewith an old man ſhould never be ſuſpected, much leſſe ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Beſides I am not ignorant that that afflicted Beauty gained her Judges, rather by her tears and by the compaſſion of her mifery, then by the luſtre of her Graces, which could not but be extinct or obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the lively apprehenſion of a death as ſhameful as her life. Philoſophy is much troubled to obſerve the ſecret cauſes of that flux and reflux of our eyes. For
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170162:14"/>to ſay that we take of the nature of that charitable Bird, which cannot behold a ſick perſon without becoming ſo her ſelf, nor be in health by a face infected with the Jaundice, is to expreſſe by an example what we comprehend not by reaſon: and though we ſhould be ſatisfied with this conſideration, and that our ſpirit would yeild it ſelf to that ſentiment, we ſhould not know nevertheleſſe the reaſon of that joy which tickles us in deploring. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that compaſſion charging us with the miſeries of another it obl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>geth us to teares, and therefore it is impoſſible, that we ſhould not cheriſh a Remedy which comforts us in part; or heales us wholly. But what! Cannot one love ſorrow with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rejoycing at it? Perhaps that ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being ordinary, and as it were natural unto us, we receive pleaſure to fool the attaint thereof from whatſoever place it comes; this familiarity is not ſo agreeable, that it may not be troubleſome: Is it not that the misfortune of our neighbour plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth us? certainly it could not cauſe in us at once contentment and pity. If we ſhould love the hurt of a miſerable perſon, me thinks we ſhould not deplore him: if we ſhould deplore him, who will believe that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170162:15"/>we ſhould love him? My Reader, I leave this curious ſearch to give you the ſubject thereof in your proper ſentiment: I fear not to put you off, ſince the tears which I promiſe you are ſweet, and ſince I am aſſured that what ſhall attriſt you, can and ought, infallibly to rejoice you.</p>
            <p>Poor <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> how the ſad ſight of your diſgraces touches my heart to the quick! And how much more willingly would I give tears to your misfortunes, then ornament to your Hiſtory! It is true, that I cannot relate your Adventures without lamenting them; and therefore if I oblige me to deſcribe them, I oblige me to deplore. That which comforts me, is, that if you languiſh through neceſſity, I ſigh with compaſſion; and that if the malice of another makes you to ſuffer, your ſole vertue cauſeth me bitterneſſe; much more when I conſider the firſt ſource of your tears, and ſee an eternal providence which travels in the accidents of your life; I draw pleaſure from your ſorrow, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you draw your happineſſe from thence. Grant then, if you pleaſe, that I diſcover to poſterity an example, which the injuſtice of the times would raviſh from it: Perhaps you will not revive un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170162:15"/>and will borrow ſome Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour from the Obſcurity which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to bury you. I fear not that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of that which afflicted you formerly, troubleth you; ſince you know perfectly, that it is the very ſame which crownes you now. Your felicity is too pure to mingle it ſelf, and your fortune too conſtant to be ſhaken. I dare like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to promiſe me, that my pen can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce you new ſentiments of joy, provided that it repreſents unto you naturally your ancient miſeries. For the motive which I give you thereof, refuſe me not the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance which is neceſſary for me to give it you: I can do nothing without your help, as I will enterpriſe nothing without your conſent.</p>
            <p>But I perceive (my Reader) that this Diſcourſe troubles you, and if I deceive not my ſelf, you would deſire to know alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the end of a Hiſtory, whereof I have not yet touched the beginning. Well then ſince you will deplore, I conſent thereto. I care not to defend you from the tears which are innocent, and which I likewiſe eſteem reaſonable. Look upon the skirt of this Wood, which the Winter hath deprived of all its beauties: approach that Rock
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170162:16"/>which thruſts forth groſſe bubbles of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and you ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd there the ſad ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of your plaints and tears. Believe not nevertheleſſe that this univerſal death which appeares to your eyes in the wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed graſſe, and upon the naked trees, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits the reſentments of a heart, which is provoked with the glory not to be inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane. That poor woman whom you ſee following a Flock, which was ſent forth from the Grange, rather to recreate then to feed, ſhould furniſh you a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Object of Piety. Her head leaning upon her right arme ſuſtained with her knee, her look immoveable, and almoſt dead, her whole countenance and her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour tell you ſufficiently that ſhe hath very little courage, or much misfortune, Ask her not her condition, grief hinders her to ſpeak; believe not that her Equipage tels it you; theſe tottered Garments that defend her from the cold, make not that ſhe is not a Princeſs: Without diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the diſgraces which have obliged her to ſerve, I think that it is enough to tel you that ſhe is miſerable, to conſtrain you to weep. Notwithſtanding I will advertiſe you that ſhe is a Saint, for fear that the exceſs of her misfortunes ſhould make you
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170162:16"/>to believe her a Criminal. Perhaps if ſhe had had leſſe innocence, ſhe ſhould have had more good fortune: but without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vining, it is certain, that her High Birth is the ſole cauſe of her great fall. Yes, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable Princeſs, I doubt not at all but your Fortune would have been better, if your extraction had not been illuſtrious: But too, who could aſſure that your Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue would have been Heroick, if your Blood had been Ruſtick? He who diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the accidents of your life, ought not to regulate his conduct upon the ſentment of thoſe that cannot conceive it. For my part, I love better to adore his Providences with ſubmiſſion, then to ſeek the Secret thereof with danger: in the one I may fear of the temerity, and in the other I ſhould hope of the merit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hirlanda</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Bretany,</hi> became conceived with child of a Son, whoſe Birth cauſed much more griefe to his Parents, then it promiſed them ſolid joyes: She was not five Months gone, but her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was conſtrained to quit her, to the end to follow the King in a War, unto which, Honour as well as his Duty called him. There are none but thoſe who are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170162:17"/>yet in the firſt tenderneſſes of a chaſte and innocent marriage, that can comprehend the rigors of a ſeparation that comes to trouble them. When the hearts are mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried as well as the bodies, there is no death whoſe convulſions would be more unpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, then thoſe of a grievous departure: Death in taking from us life and ſight, takes from us the ſentiment of all that which we love; but a departure or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence leaves us eyes only to repreſent unto us the things which can diſpleaſe us. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> (ſo will I name an unknown, ſince that name is ordinary in the houſe of <hi>Bretany</hi>) being upon the point to depart, employed all the reaſons which could conſolate his Spouſe.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Madam (ſaid he unto her) I am not ignorant that you know me too well to believe that any thing of the world ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates me from you, but the ſole ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to obey my Soveraign. Since the time that heaven conjoyned us, it hath made me to diſcover ſo many vertues in your ſoul, that I obſerve no more perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in your body: and really I may ſay unto you, that both the one and the other tye me ſo ſtrongly unto you, that if diſobedience could be honourable,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170162:17"/>your conſideration would perſwade me that it ſhould be juſt. That which aids me to overcome my repugnance, is that I know you would eſteem me unworthy of you; if I ſhould looſe an occaſion, wherein I may acquire glory in witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing my fidelity: by the contempt which I make of dangers, you will compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the account which you ought to make of my Love; ſince I proteſt unto you, that I forget the care to conſerve my life, but will never loſe the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of my dear <hi>Hirlanda.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Though the Prince was generous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, his tears and ſilence witneſſed a little weakneſſe, when he perceived that his wife began to grow tender, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing to ſpeak unto her, he continued to afflict her. It is better to break off briskly then to unwind ones ſelf leiſureably in the occaſions wherein we fear to ſhew forth leſſe courage then affection. <hi>Artus</hi> made uſe of this counſel: for feigning that his Journey was not preſſing, he went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the next morning at the break of day, leaving a Gentleman to bring him the plaints and regrets of the Dutcheſſe. But ſurely it was impoſſible for him to be faithful in his report; becauſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170162:18"/>her tears well, he ought to have her love. One of the principal recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations which the Prince left with his wives Domeſticks; was to have a great care of the Burthen ſhe went with, and ſpeedily to advertiſe him of the ſucceſſe of her Child-bed, in caſe that he ſhould be abſent at that time.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the Duke advanced towards <hi>Paris,</hi> and the Princeſſe continued her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grets, I think it is not amiſſe to withdraw us both from the one and the other, ſo ſhould we not contribute any thing to the Voyage of <hi>Artus,</hi> nor to the conſolation of <hi>Hirlanda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conceive the ſtrange accident which was to arrive in <hi>Bretany,</hi> it is fit to paſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England.</hi> It is in that ſland, which anciently bare the name of <hi>Albion,</hi> and changed it as often as the War made her to change Maſters, that the tempeſt is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med which I fear. The Duke had a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at <hi>London,</hi> who was bred up at the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Court: Were it that his inclination had made him a ſtranger, or that intereſt had ſuggeſted unto him to ſeek ſupport againſt his blood. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it was, <hi>Gerard</hi> was abſent (that was his name) when the Prince was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170162:18"/>to enterprize a long voyage. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the ſubject which made him to viſit his Country again.</p>
            <p>I know not how it happeneth, that the moſt puiſſant Monarchs of the world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not defend themſelves from the common weakneſſes of nature; their Scarlet exempts them not from the Purples, nor their Guards aſſure them againſt the other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies. But if we ſee with admiration that they are ſmitten with a diſeaſe, which for having the boldneſſe to attach Kings, takes inſolently the name of Royal, there is no cauſe to wonder, when the infirmities of the baſeſt popularity perſecutes them. It is a ſpectacle worthy of pity, to ſee a Prince gnawn with vermine, and to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand from Hiſtory, that he who ſpake like a God, was eaten up of Lice, as the moſt miſerable of his ſlaves. <hi>Henod</hi> is not the only example which we have of theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſters; even thoſe who have merited fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours from heaven, have not been diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from theſe miſeries of the earth. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> for whom the eternal Providence prepared ſo many Miracles and Victories, was he not ſeen halfe corrupted with the Leproſie? All thoſe that ſtudied his health, could not cure him, nor preſerve
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170162:19"/>him from that filthy and ſhameful infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. There was no remedy which was not uſed, but there was not any which was not unprofitable. He that healed <hi>Naaman</hi> in <hi>Jordan,</hi> reſerved unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that Cure. Learne, ye Powers of the earth, learne, that God can humble Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that if you have the temerity to diſpleaſe him, he hath the power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy you: There needeth but the leaſt of his winds (as ſaid the holieſt of our Monarchs) to ſink the King of <hi>France;</hi> at a leſſe rate then that, he can bring you to reaſon; one ſpark of his fire can burne you, and one drop of his waters drowne you: if he will, the Feaver dryes you up; if he will, the Dropſie ſplits you; and yet though your life be ſubject to theſe feeble accidents, that proud Pomp which diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth but the outſide, makes you to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume much of your Greatneſſe. You inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently think that you are not beneath your Creatour, becauſe you are a little above the other Creatures: the hurt that you may do unto them, perſwades you that you ought not to fear any thing from his arme, and that yours hath nothing which can ſtop it; as if there were a great glory to be able to do unto others, what
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170162:19"/>they may ſuffer from them. Know then once again, that you have a Maſter who brings down the proudeſt heads by the ſole will of deſtroying them, nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to reſtrain his hand, nor to change his counſel.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time that the brother of <hi>Artus</hi> was in <hi>England,</hi> he who was the Soveraign of that Land, was touched with ſo obſtinate a Leproſie, that the diſeaſe ſeemed to derive ſuccour and force from the remedies which were imployed to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh it. That poor Prince ſeeing that all the induſtry of his Phyſicians advanced as little his Cure as his Hopes, he cauſed a Jew to be called, whoſe knowledg was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much in reputation in all his Kingdom. As he expoſed unto him his Diſeaſe, and implored his aid, this Miſcreant, who would not employ malice, if it had not all the blackneſſe whereof it could be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, demanded ſome dayes to ſtudy his infirmity. A while after, this Jew retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Palace loaden with a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Remedies; which the King uſed; whilſt the quacking of his <hi>Eſculapius</hi> could deceive his confidence. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Leproſie was of another nature then that of the Jewes, who are more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170162:20"/>to that malady, then any Nation of the earth, or that in truth this Phyſician was but a Mountebank; he vexed himſelf to ſwallow ſo many loathſome Potions, and to ſee himſelf lanced every day, as was almoſt inſufferable.</p>
            <p>The Jew, who perceived it, making uſe of this device, but to maintaine his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, took occaſion to repreſent to his Patient, that his Infirmity being ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, his Majeſty ſhould not wonder if the Medicine indeavoured unprofitably to ſuccour him; that for his part he had a conceit that there was Witchcraft in his indiſpoſition: notwithſtanding, that hee ſhould not deſpair of his health, provided that his impatience made him not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt his skills: He added, that that great God who had given him ſo much power upon Nature, had not denyed him to do ſomething againſt Magick: But if he would be courageous to take a Remedy which he would preſcribe him, he ſhould have no leſſe docility to believe without examination the infallible vertue thereof. The King who feared not to drink poiſon, provided he might have hopes to be cured, interrupted a Diſcourſe which troubled him almoſt as much as his Diſeaſe.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170162:20"/>
            <p>My good friend (ſaid he unto him) I pray thee comfort my body, and amuſe thee not to perſwade my ſpirit; I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to do whatſoever thou wilt; command only, and thou ſhalt be obeyed. I put no bounds to my ſubmiſſion, whilſt I may ſee ſome aſſurance in thy promiſes.</p>
            <p>Is it fatal unto Princes who are infected with Leproſie, to meet alwayes with Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians that oblige them to be cruel for to be ſound, and to loſe humanity to acquire a little good health? He who treated with our Patient, failed not to repreſent unto him, That the firſt Emperour of the Chriſtians (whatſoever the Hiſtory ſayes of it) was cured of a Diſeaſe like unto his, by ſuch a Remedy as he prepared. And not to entertain you unprofitably with vain words, Know, Sir, that you ſhall be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, if you can reſolve to waſh your ſelfe with the blood of a little child. There is nothing more eaſie (interrupted the King.) Then can I proteſt unto you (replyed the Jew) that there is nothing in the world, more powerful againſt that corruption which ruines you. This malady having its firſt ſource in the maſſe of the blood, we muſt indeavour to put it againe into its proper and natural conſtitution: No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170162:21"/>can more contribute thereunto then a pure blood, and mingled with all kinds of qualities enemies, for as much as our great Maſter teacheth us, that one contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is cured by another. But becauſe this Remedy is exteriour, and the Diſeaſe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth the interiour of the body, we muſt aſſiſt it in taking ſomething that may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter it even in its retreat. The King pined with impatience to hear ſo many words, and to ſee ſo little effect; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure thee, my friend (ſaid he) finiſh ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, or I dye. To that which I have ſaid (anſwered the Jew) you muſt adde the heart of the fame Infant, eating it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry warm, and if it can be, yet panting. The Prince, who thought not to find a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Remedy, provided that it was poſſible, reſented ſome horrour, when he heard, that to recover his health, he muſt become Antropophage. But ſurely his ſpirit entred into very great perplexities, when he underſtood that that Infant, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for his Cure, was to be of high Birth; and much more, when he was told, that the Waters of Baptiſme would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> away from his blood, the vertue which the Jew aſſured to be natural againſt the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie. What reſolution ſhould a poore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170162:21"/>ſick perſon take, who is deceived with the good opinion of his Phyſician, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with the deſire of his health? Whatever repugnance ours reſented, he reſolved to omit nothing that might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore him, perſwading himſelf that the life of a Monarch more imported the good of the State, then that of all the young Lords that were in his Iland, Is there any thing that is unjuſt (ſaid he) when it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? So is it that the Theology of the great ones concludes when they love better the intereſt of their fortune, then the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their conſcience.</p>
            <p>But alas! Where is that innocent Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctime, which is to dye? Perhaps it is not born, yet, although they kill it already: Perhaps it playes in the boſom, of its mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and taſteth the ſweetneſſe thereof, whilſt crueltie meditates to make it drink the laſt gall of Nature.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever thou art little Innocent, thy misfortune toucheth my heart; and I cannot behold thy blood without ſhedding my teares. Finiſh not thy Birth, if thou art not in the world, or haſte to dye, if thou art in the armes of the Nurſe. On how much better were it for thee to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh then to appear: Death will be more
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170162:22"/>favourable unto thee, the leſſe life it leaves thee.</p>
            <p>And you, poor mother, Was it well done of Nature not to give you ſome fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of your griefs? I conjure you, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not to ſee that dear child, which is formed in your womb: It will be the ſweet and the ſorrowful ſubject of your afflictions: it will be the innocent Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutour of your heart, and the deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cauſe of your Martyrdome; but I am to blame to trouble the contentments that raviſh you. Poor Mother, I am to blame to draw you from that ſweetneſſe, which glues you to that Infant. Haſte you to taſte all the pleaſures that you can. Kiſs thoſe little eyes, preſſe thoſe cheeks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt yours, hide all that amiable babe in your heart, if you can. Perceive you not that it witneſſeth by its tremblings and quiverings, that it fears, or that it loves? See you not how it preſſeth upon your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, how it laboureth to enter once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain there? Deſolate mother, Look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe little eyes; do they not tell you that that poor Innocent is going to dye? and that mouth which cannot ſpeak yet, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth it not by its ſilence; the adieu which it gives you, and the cruelty which it expecteth?</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170162:22"/>
            <p>Without doubt you are curious to know the newes of our Duke, and of our Dutcheſſe.</p>
            <p>Before you may underſtand it from me, my Reader, I pray you to obſerve in the brutiſh Diſcourſe of our Jew, the true features of Superſtition. Why muſt there be an Infant of an illuſtrious houſe? Why muſt not this little Prince be baptized? Perhaps that Nobility is a Simple againſt the Leproſie? Perhaps that a water which hath received the Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of heaven, takes from the blood its natural vertue? No, believe it not, the Divel who preſides at this Cure, pretends to kill a ſoul, and not to heal a body. All theſe conditions ſerve but to envelope his deſigne, and to give colour to his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice.</p>
            <p>Let us return to our ſubject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hirlanda</hi> prepares her ſelf to lye in, all her Court made Devotions and Prayers for her happy deliverance; there was no perſon that deſired not a little Maſter, no body that begged it not of God. Whilſt that all things were between hope and fear in <hi>Bretany, Artus</hi> who was already come to the Army, ſuffered cruel tortures in his ſoul; continually the Image of his dear
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170162:23"/>Spouſe came to ſeek him, and to bring him new affrights from her: now he flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered himſelf with the hope of a quick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, and annon he afflicted himſelf with an apprehenſion that he ſhould never ſee her more.</p>
            <p>I will not conceal from you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident which cauſed him much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. One day as he was in an ill humour more then ordinary, he of his Domeſticks that opproached him with moſt confidence, having ſurprized him in this condition, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured him to diſcover unto him what cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his grief. The Prince, who uſed not to hide his heart from this Favourite, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed unto him, that the precedent night he had had a dream, which held him in great inquietudes. I was not throughly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep (ſaid he unto him) but it ſeemed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, that I ſaw my poor <hi>Hirlanda</hi> ſtretched out dead upon her bed, and a cruel Vulture ſeized upon her belly, and tore out her bowels. No body appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſuccour her; for though at times a very feeble motion, and ſome languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſighs made me believe that ſhe lived, there was about her but two Harpies, which with their tallons and ſight aſſiſted that dreadful Bird, whoſe horrible figure
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170162:23"/>preſenteth it ſelfe continually to my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory. Behold the ſubject of my ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and that which afflicteth me ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly.</p>
            <p>As he continued his Diſcourſe, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner, who was a man very capable, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented himſelf in his chamber, from whence he endeavoured to retire, when he percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them in private conference. But <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> who was touched with the curioſity to be inſtructed, and with the deſire to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert himſelf, commanded him to enter, and then having related unto him his Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he conjured him to tell him what he thought of it. The Almoner, who had no leſſe modeſty then capacity, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate not to excuſe himſelf, beſeeching his Excellence to believe, that as he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes deſpiſed <hi>Artemidorus,</hi> he never im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed either his time or paines to ſtudy him; notwithſtanding he ſaid, that he would willingly adventure to tell him what Theology permitteth to believe thereof, which he thought not unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſince oftentimes we attribute too much or too little unto Dreames. Behold his Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>My Lord, Since it pleaſeth your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to hear what I have ſometime learned
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170162:24"/>upon this Subject, I moſt humbly beſeech you to believe, That only my incapacity will obſtruct your full ſatisfaction; and that if I were more knowing, you ſhould be more enlightned: And not to divert me from your intention, I think it cannot be ſaid, that Dreames which are the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſoul, that formes it ſelf di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe figures, or receives them, ſhould be all falſe illuſions or infallible truths<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever reſpect the profane have had for the vaine Science which is made of it, the wiſeſt ſort of people mock equally the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, and the Incredulous, <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> whoſe humour is not to believe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good caution, could not approve the opinion of his Maſter, who would that all the Dreames of the night came from the Gods, and therefore that they ſhould be Celeſtial and Supernatural inſtructions for men: And to ſpeak truth (as he obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth) the Dogs and other Beaſts dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as well as we, there is little likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, that ſuch high Majeſties would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe themſelves to inſtruct Brute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> who alwayes profeſſed himſelf a great partaker of the Platonicks, makes dreams to be born in the ſoul from the ſympathy of its motions to the courſe of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170162:24"/>
               <hi>Syneſes</hi> acknowledgeth a certaine ſpirit, which I know not, that ſerves them for ſeat and carriage, in the ſame manner as the naturalliſts conduct vigour and life into all the parts of man: Others make them to ſlide from the ſtars, and ſome dare boldly to aſſure that the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of our ſpirit, are but the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances of the knowledges, which it brings from without into our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
            <p>It cannot be denied but <hi>Hypocrates</hi> hath better found out the ſource and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of them, when for the moſt part hee attributes them unto Nature, and ſometimes to its Author: he had ſaid all, if he had added, that the divels atingle themſelves very often in our ſleep; it is true, that having not diſtinguiſhed the evil genius from the good, we ſhould confound theſe two divers cauſes. That there comes unto us dreames from nature, the experience of all the nights teacheth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that God ſends them often enough, the holy Scripture inſtructeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in it. Who would be ſo raſh as to conteſt, that thoſe of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of <hi>Iſaak,</hi> of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and of <hi>Joſeph</hi> (without ſpeaking of that other <hi>Joſeph</hi> of the new Teſtament)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170162:25"/>ſhould not be the advertiſements of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to theſe illuſtrious Patriarks? I enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize not to verifie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the divels make men to dreame; and that ſometimes, to give them ſome beliefe of their Divinity, they give them preſentments of their good or evil fortunes. There is not any one that knowes never ſo little the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane hiſtory, who is ignorant of that which is related of <hi>Podalirus</hi> in the <hi>Poüille</hi> of <hi>Naples,</hi> of that of <hi>Serapis</hi> in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and of <hi>Eſculapius</hi> at <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus.</hi> Who hath not heard ſpeake of the Chappel of that <hi>Paſiphaé,</hi> which was adored in the ſuburbs of <hi>Lacedimon,</hi> and beyond <hi>Venus de Gaze,</hi> where the young maids went to dream the adventures of their Lovers? without doubt this infamous commerce, which continues yet to this day with the divels, upon the ſucceſſe of marriages, hath no other beginning but in theſe ſacriligious obſervations of the idolaters. We know but too much the impurity of theſe devotions: for thoſe that propoſe to themſelves other ends then to know marriages, behold the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of them.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that conſult the divels, after they have ſacrific'd a black ſheep unto them,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170162:25"/>wrap'd themſelves round about with his skin, and ſlept ſo in their temples, to the end, to oblige them both by their confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and liberality, to diſcover unto them in dreames, what is to arrive unto them: I confeſſe, that theſe falſe divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties expected not alwaies, that theſe poor blinded ſouls ſhould render them ſuch ridiculous homages, as if they were provoked to prevent their merit, they devanced ſometimes the devotions. And therefore when <hi>Socrates</hi> dreamed that he entred into the town of <hi>Phthia,</hi> which was interpreted of his death, becauſe that word ſignified corruption, his Gods uſed magnificence. And when <hi>Odatis</hi> loved her dear <hi>Zariader,</hi> and <hi>Zariader</hi> his faire <hi>Odatis,</hi> without ever ſeeing one another but in a dream; and that a while after that <hi>Infanta</hi> preſented the viol of gold, (which was to chooſe her a husband) to that young Prince, who appeared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known in her chamber, it was an effect of their impulſion, rather then of her pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. I ſpeak not of <hi>Alexander,</hi> who dreamed the taking of <hi>Tyre,</hi> in ſeeing a <hi>Satyre</hi> in his ſleepe, as thoſe Divines in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret it, becauſe that <hi>Satyros</hi> ſignifies in the Greek language, <hi>Tyre is thine.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170162:26"/>Did not <hi>Const<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntius</hi> alſo receive an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement of his diſaſter, going againſt the <hi>Sarazines,</hi> when he imagined in his ſleep that he went forth of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> whoſe ſylables (divided) make theſe three words, <hi>Theſ al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o nequin,</hi> leave the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to another. When <hi>Astia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſaw a vine to come forth from the belly of <hi>Mandana,</hi> and the mother of <hi>Augustus</hi> believed that her bowels were carried away unto heaven, the divels pretended to put themſelves in credit by the preſages of a greatneſſe, which they promiſed in dreames, and which the true God deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them in truth.</p>
            <p>But to the end that theſe events and ſuch others as reſemble them, may not carry our ſpirit to believe that all our dreames are true, it is fit to conſider what conjectures wee may innocently draw from them: and to ſpeake in few words what I think thereof, it is certain, that we ought as little to ſuſpect the truth of the dreames which come from God, as to receive thoſe which come from the divels, though ſometimes they be free from impoſture; the reaſon is, that we owe our beliefe unto God, and our contempt to the divels. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170162:26"/>it appertaineth not to every one to judge of theſe nocturnall viſions, prudence obligeth us to leave the diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof to thoſe that govern our conſciences. In regard of the naturall dreams, whither they proceed from the reflection which the ſoule makes upon its paſſed actions, or that they have their principle in the habitude of the body it is evident that one may recollect without crime what is to arrive unto us, ſince the humour which commands within us is the neceſſary cauſe thereof, and the reſt of our precedent actions, may be the ſigns of thoſe which are to follow. Behold the bond or annexion of the accidents of our life with our dreams, &amp; conſequently the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation which they give to the preſages which we draw from them. Dreams pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed for the moſt part from the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the temperament forms our manners, our manners have an aſcendant upon out actions in that they produce them or rule them; our journal actions have much relation and power upon the effects, whoſe cauſes are ſecret to us. There is no magick then but the ſpirit ſees our accidents in our dreams, provided, that one aſſures not this infallible ſight. So
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170162:27"/>we learn from the conduct of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Fathers, that one may form proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble judgments, not from the act, but from the inclination of the vice, or of the vertue of a perſons dreames. Behold upon what foundation a man that feares to ſinne, even in his ſleepe, and reſiſts the filthy imaginations thereof, can aſſure himſelf that he loves purity, and that an unlawful pleaſure ſhould be troubled to ſurpriſe his reaſon when it awakes. The conjectures which concern not the liberty are leſſe ſuſpected: therefore it may bee believed that he who dreames but of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant things is of a ſanguine humour, that thoſe in whom <hi>Phlegme</hi> predominates, have in their viſions but water, ſhipwrack, raine and ſnowes; the cholerick makes ſtill almoſt warre, during the profound peace of his repoſe: and the melancholy ſees not but ſorrowful objects, and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble phantoſmes. Thus the phyſicians can prudently judge of the intemperature of the humour, by the aſſiduity of dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame things. Now the reaſon why we know better the exceſſe of the temperament of that which paſſeth in the night then the day, it is that the humour ſuffers not any diverſion in its operations,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170162:27"/>whilſt the ſoule repoſes, and that being not imployed in her moſt important actions, ſhe ſuſpendeth not thoſe of the body, which follows ordinarily her application. I pretend not to deny, that the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar ſource of our dreams, is in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments and buſineſſes of the day; becauſe that the ſpecies thereof being yet fully freſh, the ſpirit, which is at leiſure, amuſeth it ſelf to review them; and becauſe that its reaſon is but half awaked, it rangeth them ſo ill, and confounds them, ſometimes with ſo much diſorder, that of the faireſt images of the day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there ſuccedeth thereof but ſtrange groteſques or confuſed repreſentations. Behold, my Lord, from whence I thinke that your dreame proceedes, you ought not then, in my opinion, to conclude that there is any thing miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous to arrive to your Lady, but rather that your imagination hath not well rallied all the thoughts which have entertained you ſince your departure from her. So ended hee his diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Thanks unto God, I have not ſo weak a ſpirit, to yeild me to the preſages of an evil dream; notwithſtanding, if the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170162:28"/>were a Monſter, cruel enough to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure an inhumane Prince, I would ſay, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate <hi>Gerard,</hi> that it ſhould be thee. I know not whether it was by hazard, or through deſign, that this young Lord was preſent at the diſcourſe of the Jew. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it was, it is certain, that all being departed from his Chamber, he went to the King, to the end to make him apprehend how much his health-imported the repoſe of his State; and that the intereſt of one ſole child ſhould not make ſo many people ſuffer. All the difficulty that ſeemed to be in the thing, was to meet with one of a fit Birth. <hi>Gerard,</hi> who played the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titian; judged that there was hazard in chuſing one of the Iland, for as much as his death might alter the ſpirit of many of his moſt faithful ſubjects. But the ſick was ſoone aſſured, by the offer which a cruel Unkle made him to releaſe him of his pain. My Reader, wonder not if I conceal you his name, I have no leſſe ſhame, then horrour to know it, and would it had pleaſed God that it had never been known in the Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>Let us withdraw from a Court<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where we ſhould be conſtrained to aſſiſt at the maſſacre of an Innocent, it is better to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170162:28"/>paſſe into that of our Dutcheſſe, where all the world rejoyced in the hope to ſee there ſuddenly a new Maſter. Though <hi>Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> had cauſe to fear her firſt throwes, ſhe expected notwithſtanding the pains there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with impatience: The deſire which ſhe had to leave a pledg of her chaſte amours to the Prince, made her to ſay a hundred times, that ſhe ſhould dye contentedly, if ſhe might give her life to a ſon, and a ſon to her Husband: The joy of all this Houſe was much augmented, when it was told to the Dutcheſſe that her Brother in Law was upon the point to arrive. As ſoon as ſhe had advertiſement thereof, ſhe ran with all the ſpeed that ſhee could to meet him.</p>
            <p>Deplorable Princeſs, What do you? Apprehend you not a fall, which it ſeemes you ſeek by your precipitation? Let us not retain her, joy tranſports her, there can be but little moderation, where there is much affection. Scarce had ſhe met this dear brother at the entrance of the Caſtle, but ſhe caſt her ſelfe about his neck: to tell you what ſhe did, it would be to tell you little leſſe then what ſhe would have done if her <hi>Artus</hi> had been returned. On the other ſide, <hi>Gerard</hi> rendred her all the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170162:29"/>which could be expected from a true amity.</p>
            <p>Madam (ſaid he at the ſame time that he feigned to be able to ſpeak) I ſhould have other then common words to expreſſe unto you my reſentments. I am raviſhed to ſee you, but I am the more ſo, in that I cannot tell it you, to ſee you in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to be one of the happieſt mothers of the earth. If I deceive me not, you are upon the point to give us a young <hi>Artus,</hi> at leaſt your Vermilion complection, and that vigour which appeareth in your whole body makes me believe that you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived nothing but what is generous. Though you have more need of a Midwife then of a younger Brother, who is not verſed therein; I rejoyce notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be at your lying in, to the end, to render you a part of the offices and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes which you ſhould expect from my Brother; it ſeemes long unto me till I hold that little Babe in my armes. (Oh Traitor! it will be too ſoon.) Beſides, I declare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, my good Siſter, that it belongs unto me to rock him, and that I will not ſuffer any body to pay him theſe petty Devoires to my prejudice. The ſweetneſſe of this Complement mollified <hi>Hirlanda</hi> in ſuch
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170162:29"/>manner, that ſhe could not reply unto him one ſole word; ſo was it better to anſwer him with the heart, then with the mouth.</p>
            <p>Some dayes ſlid away in good cheer, and preparatives for the Lying in; nine months being now even fully accompliſhed ſince the Conception of the Dutcheſs. The good mother would her ſelf prepare the little ſwadling cloaths, and other movea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles for her dear Infant, Whilſt this happy day advanced, what did <hi>Gerard?</hi> He put on the beſt countenance he could to beget in the Dutcheſſe a perfect confidence of an unfeigned Amity. But alas! Heart of man, how perfidious art thou? At the ſame time that his ſiſter made him all the Entertainment that ſhe could, he mingled with it the moſt dangerous perplexity that her Innocence could fear. The Midwife and Nurſe, who attended the Birth of that little Prince, were already in <hi>Hirlanda</hi> her houſe; ſince the arrival of her Brother in Law; theſe were the two women that he attempted, but with ſo much cunning, that his conduct paſſed in the beginning for a ſimple deſign only to affectionate them to the ſuccours of his ſiſter, and to the eares of her child. He adviſed them notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to diſcover nothing of his Lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170162:30"/>to the other Domeſticks; for feare that his favour might put them into jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; nor likewiſe to his Siſter, leſt that it might paſſe with her in ſtead of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence which ſhe deſtined them. At laſt, after a long practiſe, judging that he poſſeſſed enough the ſpirit of theſe Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary ſouls, he declared unto them that their fortune depended on their courage, and that if they had never ſo little heart, they might hope good fortune enough. The aſſurance to put themſelves in place where they ſhould have nothing to feare, gave them the boldneſſe to enterprize any thing. And then all that he demanded from their fidelity, was to feigne that his ſiſters child was dead in her labour, and to follow him in a Country, where he preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to cauſe it to be brought up, for great reaſons, which obliged him to withdraw it from its mother.</p>
            <p>At laſt the very moment of lying in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, the Convulſions thereof were ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent for the ſpace of a day, that it was ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily believed, that nothing would proceed thence, but the death of the poor Princeſs. It is true yet, that ſhe was delivered in a ſwoun, which gave opportunity enough to thoſe whom <hi>Gerard</hi> had gained, to betake
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170162:30"/>themſelves to the ſea, where a Shallop at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended them. They were to imbark in a place of the <hi>Armorick,</hi> which at this day is called <hi>Quidalet,</hi> and was then named <hi>Alethe,</hi> a word which in its Orginal ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>Errour,</hi> this place merited formerly ſo much veneration from the Inhabitants of theſe coaſts, that all the ſlaves which the tempeſt brought to this Sanctuary, reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their liberty as ſoon as they touched the borders of that happy Land. But this good fortune hapned not to thoſe that ſtole away our little Prince, for ſcarce were they entred into their Shallop, but a troop of armed men boarded them; their angry Viſages, and their naked ſwords ſhined ſo bright amidſt the darkneſſe, which the firſt break of the day had not fully diſſipated, that our Fugitives could draw from thence but a fatal preſage of their ruine. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them then Captives, and loaden with Irons in a place where the moſt miſerable quitted them: Theſe poor people ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with an accident, which they had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther apprehended nor foreſeen, doubted whether they ſhould lament or bleſſe their very fortunate misfortune. The know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which they had of their Crime gave them too much fear of the puniſhment, to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170162:31"/>rejoice at this favourable diſaſter. On the other ſide, ſeeing themſelves delivered from a death which they began to taſte when they were arreſted, it was impoſſible that the preſent joy ſhould not put ſome good interval to the fears which their evil conſcience furniſhed them.</p>
            <p>Adoreable providence of God, which conducts ſo wiſely the misfortunes of the wicked, that it leaves them fear enough in the bottom of their hearts to puniſh them, and confidence whereby not to yeild themſelves to deſpair. My Reader, You know the juſt Motive of their apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but you are ignorant for a while of that of their joy; be not troubled with that which is to arrive to our Fugitives, there is but one Innocent amongſt them: Perhaps theſe Strangers that hold him, will have pity of his miſery. But though they ſhould want ſweetneſſe to ſpare his life, the death which they ſhall make him ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, will be a favour to him; both becauſe it will be more humane then that which they deſtine him, and becauſe he is leſſe ſenſible of the grief, then he ſhall be, if compaſſion permits him to grow up. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of them who have carried him away, there is nothing too cruel and rigorous
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170162:31"/>that may arrive unto them: let their Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats have all the ill will that the ſea hath ever maintained, it will not be too much to puniſh them. I would not have you to conſider a poor mother in the convulſions of death; I would not have you think of the intereſt of a Prince, who is not yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate, but with the foreſight of his misfortune. It is ſufficient to make you conſent to the death of the guilty, to put you in mind of their Treaſon. Without doubt ſervants merit not for the moſt part the outrages which they receive from their Maſters: if they are faithful, they ought to be humane to them. But if avarice or ſome other paſſion takes from them that quality which hinders them to be our moſt dangerous enemies, becauſe they are our Domeſticks, I think that we cannot have too much ſeverity to puniſh them: But if nothing obligeth us to their pardon, when their infidelity toucheth but our goods, who could give us a thought of goodneſſe in their behalfe, when their rage aſſaulteth our honour, or our lives?</p>
            <p>Poor <hi>Artus,</hi> it is now that you ſhould ſee your dear <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> either dead, or dying upon her bed; it is now that you
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170162:32"/>ſhould find a Vulture and Harpies about her. It is true, that they are gone, and that there reſts nothing by the deſolate Princeſſe, but the marks of their cruelty on her diſgraced face, and in her languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eyes.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the ſorrowful Lady came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to her ſelf, and that grief permitted her to ſigh, ſhe demanded her child. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, Madam, (replyed one of her women) be not curious to ſee him, he is in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion more capable to give you horror then conſolation. It is no matter (ſaid the poor mother) let him be brought unto me. You will dye then (anſwered that ſubtil Wretch, who had all the intentions of <hi>Gerard</hi>) at a leſſe rate then that. I think that you ſhould not fix your eyes upon a body half formed, or to ſpeak better, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a lump of fleſh, which denotes as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle life as humane ſhape; they have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy caſt it into the earth. My dear Girle, tell me at leaſt, is it Chriſtian? Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, you ſhould ask, if it be Man.</p>
            <p>Let us not ſtay by this unfortunate Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, ſhe enters again into the Agony of her Trances, but it is to bring forth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſighs and plaints. I aſſure you, my Reader, that there is no leſſe trouble
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170162:32"/>to expreſſe them then to hear them, and that it is equally impoſſible for me to be the Spectatour thereof, and the VVriter. To offend neither your eyes or ears, I think it is fit to withdraw us from <hi>Hirlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da's</hi> chamber, for I am perſwaded, that you deſire to underſtand the Adventures of our poor little Infidel. Whatſoever curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity preſſeth you, you muſt know many things before that: and really, though we are troubled to ſee the miſeries of our Dutcheſſe, it is fitter now that we are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to her evils, to ſuffer them in company, then ſo diſcretely to husband our grief. I conjure notwithſtanding the Reader, if it happens that he deplores with her, not to blame me of hardneſſe; it will not be the Artifice of my Diſcourſe, nor the force of my expreſſion, that ſhall oblige him to this reſentment, but only the cruelty of her fortune.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs was not yet up of her Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, but her brother in Law began to give her more open proofs of his ill will; firſt by an uſage very rude, and then by words extremely injurious. O God, what a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el diſpleaſure is it to a mother, to reproach her, that ſhe is the Homicide of her fruit! This was notwithſtanding the Crime
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170162:33"/>wherewith <hi>Gerard</hi> accuſed his ſiſter, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that if ſhe had had as much love for her husband, as ſhe had for a certain Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman her neighbour, ſhe would not have ſo ill husbanded the hopes of her houſe.</p>
            <p>Poor <hi>Hirlanda!</hi> What can you ſay to theſe ſorrowful newes? But what could you do when you perceived, that the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices of your cruel brother in Law had changed the ſpirit of all your Domeſticks? That of the Dutcheſſe was not malicious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to penetrate the intricacy of that conduct; behold the natural recital there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. There was amongſt the women of <hi>Hirlanda</hi> a Damoſel, who had alwayes had her principal confidence; it was ſhe that contributed moſt to her ruine. <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard</hi> having known the weakneſſe of that maid, he gained her in ſuch ſort to his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that he diſpoſed of her more abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely then modeſty and fidelity would allow her. This was the confident he made uſe of to affright her Miſtreſſe, an hundred times a day ſhe caſt new fears in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her ſoul, as if ſhe had diſcovered the ſecrets of <hi>Gerard. Hirlanda</hi> knew well that her Brother had very much altered her Husband againſt her, which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170162:33"/>unto her by a letter, whoſe outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious complements made of her eyes two living ſources of tears: Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the Duke had not ſpoken ſo clearly, that he could content <hi>Gerard,</hi> nor aſſure the Princeſſe; but if he gave cauſe of fear to his wife, he furniſhed the means to embroile his brother. He did it with too much ſucceſſe; for that curſed confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, having told her a hundred times, that that young Prince had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from <hi>Artus</hi> to put her to death, ſhe caſt ſuch an apprehenſion into her minde, that having no other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel but fear, ſhe reſolved her ſelfe upon a flight.</p>
            <p>Co poor Princeſs, go amongſt the launds and forreſts, though you may find there Bears and Wolves, you ſhall find nothing ſo cruel as a brother in law. The deſire which I have that thoſe who have began to peruſe this hiſtory, may finiſh it, obligeth me to ſay nothing of the ſorry equipage of our fugitive, becauſe I am aſſured that the recital which I ſhould make thereof, would give more deſire to deplore, then curioſity to read. Let us let <hi>Hirlanda</hi> go.</p>
            <p>I know not whether <hi>Gerard</hi> was raviſhed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170162:34"/>with the reſolution which his ſiſter had taken; for as much as he believed to have in her flight ſtrong proofs againſt her innocence: he made ſemblance not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding to make ſearch for her, to the end, that <hi>Artus</hi> might not ſuſpect him of colluſion in his carriage. After a diligence which might beget a beliefe that he had ſought her, he would go unto the Duke himſelf to be the meſſenger of ſo many wretched tidings: it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to touch by parcels the addreſſes which he uſed to aſſiſt the jealouſie of his brother. I fear already, that I have left an ill example to poſterity, without needing to leave it ſuch particular inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of malice. Perhaps ſome one will find it very ſtrange, that <hi>Gerard</hi> imployed not poiſon to rid himſelf of his ſiſter: without doubt there is cauſe to wonder at it, ſince he had rage and baſeneſs enough. Notwithſtanding, to examine well his conduct, we have wherewith to praiſe his evil policy; for his deſign being to enjoy the inheritance of his brother: he would not give him the means of having heirs, in leaving him the liberty to chuſe another wife. Behold then a man in a new celibat, from whence he was not ſure to come
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170162:34"/>forth till after ſeven years, which the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of our anceſtors deſtined to the uncertainty of widow-hoods.</p>
            <p>I ſhould amuſe my Reader with things which would give him impatience, if I would relate what paſſed in <hi>Hirlanda</hi>'s houſe, fince ſhe quitted it. In my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is better to ſeek our unhappy Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, then to inſtruct ones ſelfe with the regrets of her unfortunate huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
            <p>He lived almoſt ſeven years in a melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholy which puniſhed ſenſibly, though ſlowly, his precipitation, when a troop of Gentlemen (his neighbours) came to take leave of him for a voyage to Saint <hi>Michel.</hi> Every one knowes that this place of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in the confines of thoſe two Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who, for being of very different humours, have need of an armed Saint to keepe them in peace. It is true, that the jealouſie to poſſeſſe ſo powerfull a Protector, would trouble their repoſe, if to content thoſe two people, the river <hi>Coeſnon</hi> loſt not his in quitting his bed, to the end, that ſucceſſively this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Archangel might be <hi>Norman</hi> and <hi>Brittain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As this Nobility of whom I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170162:35"/>had rendred theſe devoirs to that Prince of the Angels, one of the moſt conſiderable of the troop named <hi>de l'Olive,</hi> took leave of his companions to viſit an aunt which hee had a little further into <hi>Normandie:</hi> he was not a little troubled to find her houſe, which a very great wood covered of all ſides, and perhaps he had not found it, if he had not met with a country woman, who put him into the path which led to the caſtle; Inform you not of her name, it ſufficeth to know that it was a poor woman, who had the care of ordering the affairs of the back Court. She had led the flocks to the field to cheer them a little; but to ſpeak truth, it was rather to weep with more liberty.</p>
            <p>One cannot eaſily expreſſe the good entertainment which our Cavalier received in the houſe of his aunt: all the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour-hood was invited to come to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to that good Ladies rejoycement. The place of that abode was one of the moſt agreeable reſidences that one could deſire to be in: but to ſpeak the truth, the winter there was a hideous, as in any other place of the earth; all the avenues thereof were ſo hindred by the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170162:35"/>waters which rouled down in its valley, that one might believe it was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out artifice that the approach unto it was forbidden: this inconvenience of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forth, obliged the company to remaine in the houſe, and to divert it ſelf in the halls and galleries. It pleaſeth me to make you participate of a paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time which meriteth your attention, ſince it can as much inſtruct your ſpirit, as it contented the eyes and ears of thoſe that practiſed it. There was a gallery in that houſe, which looked upon the Eaſt, where all the Promenades of winter were formed. Thoſe who had given them deſign, had ſuggeſted them ornament. All the walls were adorned with excellent pictures; but one ſhould offend the Miſtreſſe of the houſe, to believe that ſhe could have ſuffered that what was but to recreate the ſight, ſhould ſerve here to wound hearts. Shee had too much charity to propoſe naked perſons to the cruel rigours of a cold which pardoned not even thoſe who were the beſt cloathed: there was not one figure which was not modeſt: the Painter himſelf had given ſo much natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralneſſe to their decencie, that one would think that modeſty animate; but if there
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170162:36"/>appeared any naked thing in the cloth, a reaſonable ſpirit would eaſily judge that the expreſſion of the hiſtory was more look'd upon then the deſign of the pleaſure.</p>
            <p>One afternoone, as all the company was in that gallery, they prayed a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding old Gentleman to decipher theſe pictures, and to ſerve for interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to thoſe ſtrangers, who ſpake to all the world without being underſtood but<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the Learned, becauſe the language of picture, though ſenſible, is mute. After a long refuſal in point of modeſty, that wiſe Seigneur, who would rather have concealed, then produced that treaſure which ſew perſons love, began his diſcourſe in theſe terms; Since you wil not conſider that thoſe of my age ſpeak ſometimes too long, I run the hazard of being trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome unto you, by the obligation which you impoſe on me to bee complacent. Your curioſity will make your patience to ſuffer: I promiſe you notwithſtanding, though I cannot content the former, that I will relieve the later as ſoon as you ſhall ſignifie to me that you deſire it. The ſeaſon invites us not to the bath, yet I muſt (without quitting that good fire)
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170162:36"/>lend you in the firſt place to that river which ſeems to flow from that cloth. Would you not judg by the inequality of thoſe floods which raiſe themſelves one upon the other, that they crowd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to fly? You comprehend well that this river is no other but the miraculous labourer of <hi>Egypt,</hi> of whom the hiſtory tels us ſo many wonders. That <hi>Nimph</hi> which you ſee at the place from whence the water ſeems to come, is it not the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Iſi,</hi> unto whoſe tears the fable at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes the inundation of <hi>Nile,</hi> which hath no other cauſe but the raines and ſnowes of <hi>Ethiopia.</hi> It is true that the young maid weeps, and therefore ſhee augments theſe waters; but beſides that, the little which ſhe contributes thereto cannot make a great inundation; ſhe hath a much truer, and more ſenſible cauſe of tears, then the death of <hi>Oſiris.</hi> I perceive the little <hi>Moſes,</hi> whom the cruelty of <hi>Phara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> hath condemned with all the Hebrew males unto ſhip-wrack; his poor ſiſter ſighes his misfortune, and attends at that river ſide, by her mothers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, the ſad ſucceſſe of his fortune; ſhe works pity in you, I make no doubt on't; let us not loſe our tears, though
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170162:37"/>after her example: though this little Prophet hath no other bark then that ruſh pannier, which is given him for a tombe, he ſhall find a happy port, becauſe hee hath God for Pilot. Behold that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe that walks upon the brink of the river with her maids, Chance brings her not there, her deſign is to bath her ſelf in thoſe wholeſome waters which make women fruitful, to the end, to give an heir unto <hi>Egypt:</hi> She ſeeks a ſon for her Father, and heaven raiſes her up a God, ſo the Scripture names this poor deſerted infant. But alas, a new danger threatens his life; I ſee him in that place where the water turns from him. It is one of thoſe monſters, to whom Nature hath not given terms of greatneſſe, perhaps, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they encreaſe alwaies in cruelty. Would you not ſay that this Crocodile hides himſelf in the bul-ruſhes, to expect his prey there, and that he opens his mouth already to devour it? Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, though the eye judges that his floods advance and conduct that veſſel into this gulfe, he ought not to fear any thing that is within; for beſides that, that this monſter is well fixed to the picture, he takes a poſture that cannot give diſtruſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170162:37"/>That bird which playes in his throat, is the little <hi>Trochilus,</hi> which we call <hi>Roytelet.</hi> There is a very ſtrait amity between theſe two animals, though farre different in humour, which ſhewes that reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance is not alwaies the mother of love. Conſider, I pray you, the pleaſure that this dragon takes in the ſervice of his little friend, who rids the teeth of the remains of his dinner. The induſtry of the Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter appeareth in this, that he expreſſeth even the pain that this ſluggiſh beaſt hath to hold up his jaws ſo long, but he witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth well that he knowes the ſecrets of Nature, ſince from the back of the bird he hath framed towards the palate of the Crocodile, a very ſharp feather, which threatens him with a wound, if he give him not leiſure to finiſh his buſineſſe. We ſhould not imagine that to make a perfect picture, the Painter wanted diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, in expoſing a Queen to that fierce animal. He knows well that the Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dile hath no crueltie in that place of the <hi>Nile,</hi> not by reaſon of that plumme which a famous Magician caſt therein, as the hiſtory will have us believe; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the abundant feeding that is there, without being obliged to ſeek it,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170162:38"/>as above <hi>Memphis,</hi> where the fiſh is ſcarce. Forget not to obſerve, that the penſil hath even put that ſecret into the countenance of thoſe women, ſince they all look upon the monſter with aſſurance. Theſe ſheep which ruminate in the ſhade of the ſedges, wherewith the river is paliſado'd, though fearful, are without apprehenſion; ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they not the wolf, that carries away one of their companions; nothing hinders him to bleat, but that crafty animal, who takes him by the throat, for fear that his cry ſhould diſcover his theft: the dogs do what they can to overtake that robber, but the perſpective hath put him ſo farre off, that their diligence is unprofitable. In the mean time the ſhepherds ſleep at their eaſe, becauſe they know not their loſſe. One would ſwear that he who leans againſt the trunk of that tree, blows; the inflation of his mouth perſwades me ſo almoſt. What ſay you of that tree which is inveloped only with one leaf of Moſſe? That fantaſie is of Art, which teacheth us by that ingenious Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſque, the natural freſhneſs of thoſe leavs, and their exceſſive largeneſs.</p>
            <p>The Interpretet made here a little pauſe, and looking about for a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170162:38"/>of the company, who was of a ſweet humour, and good wit, he ſaid unto her, I fear that you have no deſire to taſte the fruits which are faſtened to that tree, for if we believe the Orientials, it is the tree of knowledg, whoſe fruit is called amongſt them <hi>Magadan, Adams</hi> apples, and really, beſides their beauty and figure, which reſembles very much our citrons, their taſte is very agreeable to the mouth, and dangerous to the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, which denoteth ſin wel, that hath ſomething ſweet in its birth.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Tablet repreſents that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous judgment which was the firſt effect of <hi>Solomons</hi> wiſedome; two women lying together in one and the ſame chamber, it happened one night, that the moſt negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſmothered her infant, whom ſhe had put in the bed by her, to give it more eaſily the teat. That which ſhe did, being awaked, ſignified enough that this accident was without deſign, and without malice; for ſcarce perceived ſhe it, but behold her at her companions bed, from whence ſhe took her ſon, ſubſtituting the dead one in his place. The morning which diſcovered this deceit, put much trouble in the houſe. Each of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170162:39"/>proteſted that hers liv'd, and that the other had rob'd her of it. <hi>Solomon,</hi> who began to be King, muſt begin to be Judg, through an affair ſo confuſed: that woman of the two which feigned beſt, ſeem'd in the judgment of all the Counſel to uphold ſolidly her cauſe. No, ſaid the young Prince, it is not juſt that one alone poſſeſſe wholly this infant, ſince the right of the one, is not more cleer then that of the other; to content them both, let it be divided. To ſee the perſonages of this picture, you would judg that this ſentence took from them all their colour and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, except from the falſe mother, who laughed with pleaſure, approving a cruelty which was favourable unto her. You know the ſubject of that picture, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you diſcover not the artifice thereof. Before you conſider it, I would fain tell you that the Painter hath committed a fault, not in his art, whoſe lawes he hath perfectly-obſerved, but in Cronologie, placing <hi>Solomon</hi> in that miraculous throne, which he built not but long time after this judgment. It is to be believed, that this happy fault was of purpoſe, and that he would rather appear <hi>Architect,</hi> then ſcrupulous in the knowledg of the times;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170162:39"/>ſo is there not a piece which is not ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, be it in the body of the work, be it in the columns, the chapters, the frize, and the reſt of its ornaments. Really, if I knew not that theſe Lions, which hold up the tribunal, are of gold and Iyroy, I ſhould fear that they were living. Let us looke but on the principal of the piece; ſhould you not ſay that theſe two old men who are by the King, do meditate the reaſons of a ſentence, which ſurpriſeth their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? In the mean time, a ſouldier of the guard takes that poor little one who lives even in the image, and holding him up by the heels, he ſtretches out his arm with ſtrength, the better to aſſure his ſtroak; his ſight is fixed upon the place where he intends to make the diviſion to render it more eaſie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> notwithſtanding he hath a corner of his eye upon the King, participating his look to thoſe two ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as if he demanded the time to let fall his ſtroke: it is this that ought to take fear from you, in that he hurts not that Innocent, who though turn'd topſie turvie, endeavours unprofitably to joyn his hands in the aire by an inſtinct of nature, who alſo turns his eyes unto heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from whence we learn at our birth, that it is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170162:40"/>from thence that our aſſiſtance comes. But I pray you to conſider how his leg and left thigh falling upon his flank, make there, with their weight, a marvellous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction. The diſtention of his ſtomack cauſed by the fall of his belly, merits no leſſe admiration, ſince it expreſſeth even the paine of the infant. That young woman which you ſee at the end of the Picture, and who holds her apron in a condition to receive the half of that body, pretends to be the mother thereof, though to ſpeak truth, there is not one feature in her face that witneſſeth it. She ſeems to have left all the fear and pity on the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of that good old woman that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows her: conſider, I pray you how fear withdraws her lips, to the end, that only one tooth which is left her may appear; her front, where every moment of her life hath plac'd a wrinkle, heaps it ſelf up in the midſt in ſuch ſort, that you might judg that all theſe lines have their center there, to mark unto her the hour of dying. Since you are neer enough to that pillar, forget not to behold that little boy, who hides himſelf under its garlands and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broideries. You believe that it is but an ornament of the hall, which is repreſented
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170162:40"/>in the picture, and yet to ſee the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that he makes to raiſe himſelf aloft, and his attention on that which is done below, you would ſay that he fears for all the little boyes. I know not if it be that child which is going to dy that makes him afraid, or he that you ſee dead in that ſquare: his lips already blue, and the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that dog, which nothing but his attachment hinders to ſent him, ſhew ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently that he is the ſorrowful ſubject of that proceſs. Good God, how the death of him that lives yet, appears na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally in the face of the true mother! one would eaſily believe that ſhe hath nothing more then theſe two words to ſay unto <hi>Solomon,</hi> Sir, I quit my part of him; ſee how ſhe ſtretches her arms be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſword and her ſon, either to ſtop, or to receive the ſtroak. You know the reſt of the Hiſtory, ſo that it ſhall not need to trouble you more: if I had not forgotten the diſcretion that I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed you, I had made an end long ſince of wronging your patience. Old men have ſhort memories, and great inclination to ſpeak, as I have already ſaid unto you: I ſhall be ſo ſhort in that which remains, that your goodneſs wil voluntarily pardon
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170162:41"/>my former tediouſneſſe. You judg with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, by theſe trees and hills which ſhew themſelves but half-waies, that the Painter repreſents us a night in his work: this deep ſilence which makes the repoſe of all Nature, ſeems it not likewiſe expreſs'd unto you by the penſil: how that hare which I perceive in that buſh gathers up himſelf perfectly in form, and how theſe little birds which cannot be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, becauſe the obſcurity makes them all of one colour, ſleep quietly. I ſhould fear that that greateſt, which a darkneſs more charged makes me take for a Mearl, ſhould tumble, if I knew not that a fall upon the wing is without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of hurt. But though the ſhadows would not mark out into you ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently a night, in lifting your eyes towards the heaven, which a pale and waſh'd Azure depaints above the Picture, the ſtars would make it appear ſufficiently. Know you not the Bear, which ſhines with more brightneſs then any other of theſe ſtars? behold a little lower <hi>Andromeda<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> behold the Swan; I know not if it be of purpoſe or by chance that the Painter hath made nothing to break but the conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which mark unto us the flight or
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170162:41"/>retrait of ſome one of the earth into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. I ſhould believe it almoſt, if he had not lightly traced the milky way, by which the Profane aſſure that the Gods go to counſel, and the Pilgrims to Saint <hi>James,</hi> us the ſimple imagine. That young wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who is mounted upon an Aſs, and holds a child in her armes, it is the divine <hi>Mary,</hi> who comes forth of that Village which you ſee in the bottome of the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture. Her poor Husband followes her, leading the Aſſe which carries all the bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage of the greateſt and moſt illuſtrious Familie of the Univerſe. Perceive you not that the darkneſſe retires at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of theſe Torches, which two An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels carry before their little Monarch. This imagination of the Painter is excellent, but his thought is better yet, ſince he pretends to inſinuate, that the Eclipſe of that divine Sun which hides himſelf in our fleſh, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to the world to diſſipate our dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. He goeth forthwith to invade that of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which is its true Country, ſince <hi>Moſes</hi> was there a miraculous night in plain midday.</p>
            <p>This laſt Tablet where I ſee the maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre of the Innocents, carries the ſubject of the flight of Jeſus and of his mother:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170162:42"/>you know too well the Hiſtory thereof to believe me obliged to make you the reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of it. Regard the Action of theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages, you may ſay, that there is not one of them which cryes not, except that poor mother, whoſe tongue the Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner roots out, to puniſh her with her grief, and to hinder her to complain. I fear to be cruel in obliging you to turne your eyes upon thoſe three Souldiers, who make a Pyramide of the heads of theſe pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Victimes. It is true, that their rage equals not that of this other, who for fear that a poor woman ſhould conceal her ſon in her belly, teares it out gaſping from her bowels. Behold another ſitting, who indeavoured to feigne that ſhe hath no fear, becauſe ſhe hath no Infant: but whilſt ſhe uſeth this innocent hypocriſie, I know not if that poor little one, fearing that he ſhould not be a Martyr, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth his arme from beneath her coat where he was hidden. One of theſe Inhumanes mocketh it, and cuts it behind, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſigne to his companion to finiſh. See (I pray you) the deſpair of that mother, who afflicts her ſelf at this, that drawing herſon from between the hands of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutioner, there remaines in her hands but
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170162:42"/>one thigh of him. Not one appeared more content then ſhe, who leaning her ſelf upon her child to cover it from the ſword, received it athwart her body. This ſad Spectacle afflicts you, I make no doubt on't, ſo will I ſtay your eyes no longer there; I deſire only that you would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the endeavour which that woman makes to withdraw hers; one would judg that ſhe puts it out of the Picture, ſo much ſally hath the Painter given it; but alas! ſhe cannot keep it from the Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſs, which cleaves it in two in the midſt of the air.</p>
            <p>Whilſt that this wiſe old man entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the company with ſo much ſatisfaction, that it would be hard to expreſſe it, it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the Chevalier <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Olive</hi> caſt his ſight upon that woman who had conducted him to the Caſtle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you would have ſaid, that all this diſcourſe had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſign but to make her weep; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, as ſhe perceived that they dooked upon her, ſhe conſtrained her eyes to an obedience, which was not very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, becauſe that from time to time her cears began again to diſtil. I can no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger forbear to tell you that this unknowne perſon was our unfortunate <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> who
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170162:43"/>for ſeven yeares remained in that houſe in quality of a ſervant; her greateſt trouble was, to let nothing appear of her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: but though her Prudence had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſuppreſſed the livelieſt ſplendour thereof, ſhe could not ſo conceal her ſelf, but her Miſtreſs diſcovered many things that made her to be conſidered. Behold that which obliged her to keep her by her, and to love her diſcourſe. It is hard for a Peaſant to act a Prince, there will often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſlip from him ſomething of the Countrey. A Perſon of Birth hath no leſſe trouble to diſſemble; though his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune ſhould bellow, his courage is alwayes high. If it happeneth likewiſe that he is conſtrained to humble himſelf to Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unworthy of his blood, it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates unto them, I know not what Grace, which ennobleth them, and hinders them to be Ruſtick Occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</p>
            <p>But alas, how much more deſiteable had it been to our Dutcheſſe, not ſo often to approach her that took ſo much pleaſure in her Service? At leaſt it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed but this laſt Encounter was fatal to her; for at laſt the misfortune of her poor child was not ſo prudent concealed but
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170162:43"/>ſome inkling thereof was come to her ears. She had heard it reported, that that deare moity of her ſelf had been raviſhed from her, that they had expoſed it to the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous waters of the ſea, and that a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Pirats had ſeiſed the veſſel that carried it away. Was not this enough to perſwade her, that theſe Pictures which were deciphered in her preſence, were but Images of her misfortune; ſo believed ſhe that the deſigne of this diſcourſe looked upon her, though there was no ſuch thought. When they ſpake of the little <hi>Moſes</hi> abandoned to the floods of <hi>Nile,</hi> Love ſaid unto her, Poor <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy poor Infant: if ſhe contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Maſſacre of the Innocents, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhe imagined that hers had met with ſome <hi>Herod.</hi> The flight of the holy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God, and her exile into <hi>Egypt,</hi> made her to remember the day that ſhe left her houſe, and her ſeven years abode in that of her Miſtreſs. She cared not to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage her grief in conſidering the happy end of the Adventures which the Painter had repreſented in his Work. She choſe not in their Hiſtory, but that which was proper to her affliction. Good God, how weak is the ſpirit of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to reſiſt an evil,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170162:44"/>and how ingenious it is to augment its troubles!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> is there nothing in all theſe Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures capable to conſolate your grief by the hope of a better fortune? Cheriſh you your misfortune ſo tenderly, that you ſhould ſeek with care the meanes to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it? I confeſſe, that the diſaſter of your ſon, cannot have more illuſtrious fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures then <hi>Moſes</hi> and thoſe other chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; but why take you only that which is evil in their Hiſtory? But if your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty makes you to believe that having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like to their merit, you ought not to expect any thing equal to the benefits which obligeth them, I conſent that you ſhould preſume little of your vertue, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that you conceive no: any diſtruſt of Gods goodneſſe. Expect not the favor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that appertain but to the Patriarks and Saints, but deſpair not of a protection, which he denies not even to his enemies. Since you cannot think that he ſaves your little Prince with the Prophets, be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that he will not deſpiſe him more then the Profane. If all theſe great mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles cannot move your ſpirit, nor ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rich Pictures leave any impreſſion in your ſentments, caſt at leaſt a light view
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170162:44"/>upon theſe hangings; you ſhall ſee there <hi>Romulus</hi> by a Wolf that gives him ſuck, and <hi>Cyrus</hi> by a dog that defends him: <hi>Hieron</hi> is expoſed here to the Hornets, and <hi>Lagus</hi> to the Vultures; but a ſwarm of Bees ſtands Sentinel for that, and an Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle for this. Forget not to conſider <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes,</hi> whom <hi>Agolmond</hi> King of the <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards</hi> raiſes from the end of his Lance to the Throne, drawing him out of a Lake where he had been caſt with his ſix twin Brothers. <hi>Hirlanda</hi> cannot ſtop her ſelf at this.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding let us not believe that this hapned without the conduct of that Providence which governes the leaſt acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of the world. I ſaid, that the Lord <hi>d' Olive</hi> perceived the Dutcheſſe teares, which obliged him from time to time to look upon her. As he conſidered her, a thought came into his mind, that ſhe was without doubt that unfortunate Princeſſe, which vaniſhed away in <hi>Bretany.</hi> She ſeemed unto him at firſt extravagant, as being not able to finde a woman of that condition in a Country Chamber-maid; notwithſtanding conſidering the features of her face and her ſtature, he concluded that he need no more doubt thereof. When
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170162:45"/>the company was retired, our Knight went to find out his Ant, and prayed her to tell him the truth. The good Lady, who knew well enough how to treat perſons of that quality, replyed unto him, that if God had done her the favour to ſend unto her a woman of that rank and merit, ſhe would not fail in the duties of a moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervant.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, not able to quit this imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he conjured her to examine that ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and to conſtrain her to declare her name and Country. Not to make unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Diſcourſes, <hi>Hirlanda</hi> confeſſed that ſhe was that unfortunate Dutcheſſe; this confeſſion changed the whole houſe, for as much as ſhe that commanded, would now obey at her turn. <hi>D' Olive</hi> failed not to render her all the reſpects that he believed was due unto her, both in regard of her Dignity, and becauſe of her vertue. Notwithſtanding they judged wiſely, that they ſhould not make this report to break forth at a clap, and prudence obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them to live in the ſame conduct, which appeared before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hirlanda</hi> was not troubled to play her part, becauſe ſhe exerciſed it many years; but ſurely our good Ant ſuffered much,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170162:45"/>when ſhe muſt act the Miſtreſſe. A hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times before ſhe was aware, ſhe ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred her great ſubmiſſions, and called her Madam in the preſence of her Domeſticks: for our Gentleman, he reſolved to paſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Bretany,</hi> to the end to diſpoſe the Duke to the return of his innocent wife: Upon the point to depart, he proteſted that he ſhould never he content untill he ſaw his Princeſſe in the honours which ſhe merited, and that he ſhould think his life wel imployed, if he might dye in maintaining her Vertue. The Dutcheſs failed not to aſſure him of the eſteem which ſhe made of his Service, but that it would be an inconſolate regret unto her to ſee him take pains to procure her content.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>My Cavaliere</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>I cannot diſſemble to you, that your good will obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth me, and that though I have not the means to acknowledge it, I have heart e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to reſent it. I owe to your Courage rather then to my Vertue, the Deſign which you take to relieve an oppreſſed Innocence; but permit me to tell you, that I more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to live unknown then juſtified, and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe covet the Dignity of a Dutcheſſe, then che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the condition of a Slave. Alas, what advantage procure you me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when you ſhall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170162:46"/>place we again in</hi> Artus <hi>houſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Perhaps I ſhall be there more happy then in the firſt yeers of my Marriage, and ſhall find ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Husband then he that threatned me with death? Doth not</hi> Gerard <hi>live ſtill? And if he lives, what ſhould I hope from him after a Turkiſh cruelty? Think you that he that chargeth me with the death of an Innocent, whom he hath maſſacred, can ſuffer a face which reproacheth his cruelty to him? Hath he not the ſame motives to hurt me, and his brother the ſame weakneſs to believe him without hearing me? O how much more deſireable is it to me to remaine unknown in a houſe where Vertue defends me from inquietudes, then to go ſeek new tempeſts, where I have never found repoſe. Would you raviſh from me the delights which I taſte by your Aunt, who is to me in ſtead of a mother, ſince I had the happineſs to be knowne unto her? Is there any thing in the Palace of</hi> Artus, <hi>which countervails the ſweetneſs which I taſte in this concealed life, where the goodneſſe of God renders it ſelf ſo ſenſible to my poor heart, that I doubt if the place of my Exile be not of my glory. But though ſo favourable a San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary ſhould be grievous unto me, and that I ſhould promiſe me more love and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170162:46"/>amongſt my own, what is there in that ſweet life that is constant and muſt not end? Believe me (my Cavaliere) that fair vanity of the Court laſts not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, we muſt ſoon or late break thoſe fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Gold, which makes ſo many volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary ſlaves. Should you have ſo little goodneſs for me, to perſwade me to put my ſelf again to a chain, from whence ſo amiable is Providence hath delivered me? When I remember the little leiſure that we have to think of God, and the neceſſity which enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth almoſt the beſt courages to abandon themſelves to the world, I have no leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnance to think of my former life, then obligation to amend the faults thereof. My Noble Sir, leave me here where I have no Jealouſie to content, no Traytor to flye, nor any troubleſom perſons to defend my ſelf from. But if I remain in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein I cannot acknowledg the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which you witneſſe to have for</hi> Hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa, <hi>believe that you oblige an unable, and not an ungrateful perſon. I dare like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to aſſure you, that God taking care to recompence you at my requeſt, you ſhal have more cauſe to bleſſe my little power, then reaſon to deſire to change my fortune.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The Knight <hi>de l'Olive</hi> was much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170162:47"/>to bring the reſolution of the Princeſs to the change which he propoſed to her. Notwithſtanding after he had excuſed the Duke of his credulity, upon this, that it is hard for a Husband to love with paſſion, and to love without jealouſie, he preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto her that the fault which he had done, and whereof he had a hundred times repented, would hold him hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward in diſtruſt of all reports that might be made him. Beſides, that being himſelf witneſſe of a vertue which was diſguiſed unto him; it would be as eaſie for him to reject the calumny, if it had impudence, as it would be hard for him to take the pretences. <q>[After all, Madam (added he) it is not ſo much your inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to paſſe again into <hi>Bretany,</hi> as that of all your ſubjects: I omit notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that their happineſſe depends of your conduct; and that never any one of your Domeſticks ſhall come forth of his miſery but by your meanes. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider only what you owe to your Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and what you owe to your ſelf. I believe that you are not ignorant that his ſafety depends partly on you, and that having charmes enough to hinder his debauches, you ſhould be guilty of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170162:47"/>them, if you remove a remedy which can cure him of it. My zeal ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the liberty which I take, to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto you your duty. For that which concernes you, I think that no body can contradict me, if I aſſure that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſuffer longer the oppreſſion of your Innocence, and that you will begin to be criminal, when you ſhall begin to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe your ſelf to your juſtification. I ſhould not care to perſwade you to your return, if I foreſaw it not glorious, and knew not that it is neceſſary for us.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As our Cavalier had ended that laſt word, the good Princeſs drawing a deep ſigh from her heart, ſaid unto him,</p>
            <p>
               <q>Well, ſince you judg it ſo, I conſent to be yet miſerable. Go, and proſper: I ſee well that my God will have me to ſuffer, endeavour to place again the poor <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> where every day ſhe ſhall be conſtrained to ſee and ſhew good countenance to the Murtherer of her child. I ſpeak not of the honour which they endeavoured there to raviſh from me: Innocent Victime, thy ſole misfortune toucheth me, becauſe thou liveſt no more.</q>
            </p>
            <p>A few dayes after the Gentleman depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170162:48"/>to obſerve the time and meanes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh his deſigne: He was not long with <hi>Artus,</hi> but he took occaſion to make him the Overture thereof. One day the Duke being at the Chaſe, as the Knight <hi>de l' Olive</hi> entertained him very much with the happineſſe of his condition, and perceived that <hi>Artus</hi> was not of his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and likewiſe that the Prince confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to him that many things were wanting to his contentment. I think, added the Cavalier, that your Excellence could henceforth deſire nothing which you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy not; but if any thing be wanting to your felicity, I ſuppoſe that it is a chaſte <hi>Hirlanda.</hi> At this word, as if one had pierced the heart of <hi>Artus,</hi> he ſent forth a ſigh thence, which declared plainly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that he had touched his inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>My Cavalier (ſaid he unto him) would to God that it was as eaſie for me to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs her, as to deſire her, I ſhould then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve my happineſſe accompliſhed, and you ſhould have cauſe to tell me, that I ought to be content. But if I cannot be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy but in the fruition of a good ſo perfect, I am ſure never to live without diſpleaſure, ſince I have no aſſurance ever
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170162:48"/>to ſee <hi>Hirlanda</hi> again. Alas, how that cruel night which raviſhed her from me, hath given me diſquiet ones! She is dead, my dear friend, and with her all my joyes are vaniſhed. And though ſhe lived, who knowes the place of her retrait? And if any one knew it, who could perſwade her to come from thence? She ſhould have goodneſſe enough to forget, that I am culpable of all the evils which ſhe endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and that my credulity hath made her fidelity to be doubted.</p>
            <p>Sir, (replyed <hi>de l'Olive</hi>) it is rather your evil fortune, then your evil will, which gives cauſe to theſe diſpleaſures. Though it touch a woman to ſee her ſelfe ſuſpected, there is left her alwayes ſo much reaſon to penetrate, that the umbrage of a husband proceeds from the exceſſe, and not from the defect of his love; and that if he were but a little jealous, he would not be very ardent. I know well that the thought which claſheth the fidelity of a wife, ſuſpects her Vertue, but alſo it wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the eſteem of her good qualities; ſo that Jealouſie offends not ſo much the Vertue of a woman, as it forbids the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes of an envious perſon. I am aſſured that your <hi>Hirlanda</hi> is ſtill yours, and that
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170162:49"/>if ſhe hath quitted your houſe, it is to conſerve you the moſt precious of your goods againſt the malice of thoſe who have endeavoured to deſtroy her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Doubt as little of her life, as of her affection: But if your Excellence pleaſe to command me to find her, I aſſure my ſelf that you ſhall ſee within a few dayes both her love and her face.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the Cavalier held this Diſcourſe, he kindled an ardent deſire in the ſoul of <hi>Artus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Cavalier (replyed lie) I think it is to no purpoſe to dream of <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> but I can well proteſt, that if ſhe lives, no body could render me a more acceptable ſervice, then to perſwade her to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne.</p>
            <p>The Gentleman ſtayed no longer to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen himſelf to the Duke in all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars that hapned to him; he related unto him how he had found his dear Spouſe in a diſguiſed habit with one of his Aunts, where ſince her Quality was known, ſhe received all the honours that were due unto her. From this time forward the face of <hi>Artus</hi> was wholly changed, there was ſeen there no other melarcholy, but that which the impatience to ſee the Dutcheſs, imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therein.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170162:49"/>
            <p>Scarce were they returned from the chaſe, but the Knight <hi>De l'Olive</hi> was commanded to paſs again into <hi>Normandy</hi> to conduct his Miſtreſſe. It is hard to expreſſe the regrets of <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> and of her good Hoſteſſe, when they were to give the laſt adieu: nothing could ſweeten their ſeparation, but the promiſe to ſee one another in the Spring. So muſt it be granted that there are no delights compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable unto thoſe of a life retired from the noiſe and crowd of the world. It is not in the dirt of towns that heaven ſheds his dew, there is but the country which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives thoſe pure favours, and can taſt them; it is there that God ſpeaks to his Elect, that he entertains them familiarly; and to ſpeak all in a word, it is there that he poſſeſſeth them without trouble. Our holy Princeſſe ſaw well what ſhe loſt, ſo witneſſed ſhee it enough by her tears.</p>
            <p>The Duke having underſtood that his wife was but a dayes journey from his houſe, he departed with a good number of Gentlemen to receive her with all the teſtimonies of a true and perfect good will. I will not tell you that there was a little confuſion in the firſt ſalutation. <hi>Artus</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:170162:50"/>could not think of his too much credulity without-bluſhings, notwithſtanding the tranſport of joy overcame all the other reſentments of his ſoul. A thouſand times he asked pardon of the Dutcheſs, proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her that the exceſs only of his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction had been the cauſe of his errour. <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> who knew well that the forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of injuries, was the proof of a good courage, gave to the Duke all the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances that ſhe could of having no remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance at all of what was paſs'd; ſhe ſought likewiſe reaſons to perſwade him that he had not offended, to the end that he might not have cauſe to fear. I paſſe lightly this firſt interview, becauſe it is impoſſible for me to expreſs the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies thereof; what I can ſay is only to aſſure that this happy day was like unto that of the Dukes nuptials; all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycements thereof were renewed. A great number of Nobles came to the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of <hi>Artus</hi> to congratulate with him his good fortune, and with the Princeſs her happy return.</p>
            <p>It ſeemed that ſo much joy could not ſuffer any ſorrow in hearts ſo content; but alas, <hi>Hirlanda</hi> ſaw not her dear ſon! her grief was without conſolation, becauſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170162:50"/>her evil was without remedy: the poor little one was dead both in the opinion of the father, who believ'd him ſmothered in his birth, and in that of the mother, who had ſome doubt of his ſhipwrack. Never caſt ſhe her eyes upon her child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, but all her trances renewed in her heart: if any one of the women which ſerv'd her formerly, preſented themſelves to her, one would have ſaid that it was to advertiſe her to weep. Oftentimes ſhe would retire her ſelf all alone into that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal chamber where her dear child had been raviſhed from her; and as ſhe ſaw her ſelf without witneſs, ſhe afflicted her ſelf without compaſſion. <hi>Hirlanda</hi> (ſaid ſhe) muſt thou live the remainder of thy dayes in a place where thou oughteſt to die? Why did not thoſe who ſnatch'd an infant from thee out of thy bowels, tear out alſo thy heart? would their pity be inhumane, and ſhew that vertue it ſelf is criminall in a barbarous foule? Oh poor victime, how deſirable would it have been unto me to expire with thee, if thou art dead; or to languiſh in thy company, if thou liveſt!</p>
            <p>My Reader, you know well that the ſon of our Dutcheſſe is not yet dead, if
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170162:51"/>there be not arrived to him ſome new accident, and more cruel then the former which aſſaulted him. I am much deceived, if I told you not that upon the point of his embarkment a troop of unknown people entred into the veſſel, and ſeized upon the traitors that carried him away, as they would caſt him into the ſea. This order came from <hi>Gerard,</hi> uncle to the little one, who judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this precaution neceſſary to the ſecret of his deſign; it is ſo, that an evil action may be aſſured, that it ſhall be ſoon or late recompenſed, even by thoſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by its malice, and that give the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel thereof. But where have they condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that band of criminals who without doubt fear to live, becauſe they merit a rigorous puniſhment, and who deſire yet to fear long, becauſe they come to ſee death? It is that which I will tell you, my Reader, provided, you will permit me to inſtruct you with a thing which you ſhall confeſſe to be for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Maloes,</hi> a Town of high <hi>Bretain,</hi> is at this day ſufficiently known by that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous garriſon of dogs which keep it by night, whilſt the floods of the ſea which
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170162:51"/>guard it the day, retire themſelvs to leave them in faction. It is a part of that ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorie, whoſe people are named <hi>Diublin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres</hi> by <hi>Pliny, Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Strabo.</hi> But beſides that, and the great traffick which it maintains, the Epiſcopal ſeat which <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alethe</hi> tranſported there in the yeer 1172 makes it to paſs for one of the conſiderable Towns of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince: four miles from St. <hi>Maloes</hi> is the famous Town of <hi>Monfort,</hi> whoſe name is great enough in the hiſtory, by reaſon of the miracle or prodigie which hath been conſtantly obſerved there for the ſpace of three or four ages, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the laſt hath ſeen the end. It is enough to name the Duck of <hi>Monfort,</hi> to make all thoſe of the country to remember, that every yeer a wilde Duck iſſuing out of the neighbouring Marſh came the firſt of <hi>May</hi> to the Church, where ſometimes more then ten thouſand perſons conducted her in proceſſion, and from whence ſhe retired her ſelf after the offering, leaving one of her twelve Ducklins to the Curate, for a monument of her natural piety. What love ſoever that bird had for her little ones, this loſſe was not conſiderable; for beſides that ſhe made a preſent unto
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170162:52"/>God, there alwaies remained unto her a good number. But alas, the unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>Hirlanda</hi> loſes her only one, and loſes him for ever, ſince the ſacred waters of baptiſm aſſure her not to ſee him again, nor ever to meet that dear moiety of her ſelf. My reader, I would fain that theſe circumſtances ſhould deſign you the place where we are to find again our little Prince.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time that the Nurſe accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with her husband, and ſome confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of him that hath gained them, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared their paſſage for <hi>England;</hi> God, who never forſaketh the innocent in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, thought of the means to take from them this precious infant. A vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable old man, named <hi>Bertrand,</hi> gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at that time the <hi>Abby</hi> of St. <hi>Maloes,</hi> which ſince is changed into a Cathedral; ſcarce had this holy man taken his firſt ſleep one night, but an Angel appeared unto him, and communded him from God to awake his ſervants preſently, and to ſend them towards <hi>Alethe</hi> to ſtop fugitives which carried away a little boy who had not received baptiſm. The Abbot, who knew perfectly the voice of him whom he was to obey, called his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170162:52"/>brother, who repoſed in another apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and with all the diligence that could be uſed, without incommodating himſelf, commanded him to execute what I have already inſinuated. It was no hard thing for people reſolv'd and well arm'd, to force five or ſix rogues, whom fear had more then half overcome; there was notwithſtanding no more but the Nurſe with her husband that was taken, holding in her arms that poor victime which ſhe carried to death: the others were either ſlain in the defence, or ſaved themſelvs in the darkneſs. Until then the Abbot knew nothing of our hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory; but he learned of the Priſoners the birth of the child, and of the Angel the ſad adventure which attended it in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> It is not to be doubted alſo, that God revealed unto him the conduct which he ſhould take for the future in its edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: though the good old man was touched with compaſſion, ſeeing the tears of the Nurſe, who confeſſed not the truth but by conſtraint, he cauſed her to be put into a priſon, where ſhe ſoon loſt her husband. This wicked woman, queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned about the parents of the child, feigned that as ſhe walked in the road, a troop of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170162:53"/>thieves had carried them away.</p>
            <p>The good Abbot could ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict her, both by the equipage of the little one, which was not conformable to thoſe of her condition, and by her tears, which without doubt would not have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed her good fortune.</p>
            <p>How admirable is our great God in his ſweet and ſecret providences! at the ſame time that our little ſtranger entred into the Monaſtery, the ſiſter of <hi>Bertrand,</hi> who had a little girle at her breſt, loſt it, as if that innocent creature had not lived until that moment, but to keep her mothers milk for him. This death cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her parents much diſpleaſure; but the Abbot, who look'd upon this, accident as a particular diſpoſition of heaven, had not much trouble to comfort them. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cauſed his ſiſter to be called, he ſaid unto her,</p>
            <p>
               <q>My Daughter, you have loſt your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hild, if it be to loſe her to reſtore her unto him who gave her you; I blame not your tears, becauſe they are juſt, provided, that they be not obſtinate. Though God could take your goods without rendring you either accompt thereof or recompence, he is notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170162:53"/>ſo good, that he would not take from you a daughter, without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you a boy in her place. Receive him from his hand by mine, and give me this proof of your amity, that you have no leſs care of his breeding, then if he were your ſon. Perhaps this abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned babe ſhall be the happineſs of your Houſe; and if God give you other children, this little miſerable may be the cauſe of their good fortune. But though you ſhould expect no other reward but from heaven; you have a motive juſt enough to do this good office to this Orphan, ſince I aſſure you from God, that he hath adopted him for ſon.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As he had ended theſe few words, he put the little <hi>Bertrand</hi> into her arms: <hi>Berita</hi> (that was the name of this vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Gentlewoman) received him with no leſs reſpects then if God himſelf had charged her with him. But that which meriteth more conſideration; ſhe no ſooner preſſed him on her boſome, but he entred into her heart, having as much tenderneſs for him, as ſhe ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented for a ſon, of whom ſhe ſhould have been the true mother I am too haſty to tel
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170162:54"/>you the name of our little one; for to ſpeak truth, he had not yet any. It was but the third day after he was received, that the holy old man give him his, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that ſhe whom he bad choſen him for Nurſe, ſhould hold him at the font with him. After the ceremony of the Baptiſm was finiſhed, and that his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother had put her dear Nurſling into his ſwadling cloaths, there happened a thing which drew tears from the good Abbot. Scarce had he that little Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in his arms, but he opened his little eyes, and then holding them fixedly ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon the venerable face of <hi>Bererand,</hi> he betook himſelf to ſmile, but in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſo natural and orderly, that one would have judged that he thanked him for his charities. The Saint knew well that children begin to laugh at the ſeventh day of their birth, and therefore this little Prince being of that term, was to give the ſame ſigns which are ordinary to thoſe of his age. Notwithſtanding, he would rather believe that this laughter was an effect of Grace, then a motion of Nature, and that he expreſſed himſelf rather Chriſtian then Man by this miraculous joy. There was no body there that grew
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170162:54"/>not tender, ſeeing the good old man to weep as abundantly upon that child, as if he were to baptize him again with his tears. He ſpake unto it ſo many things as was ſufficient to make one ſwoun with tenderneſs, but he ſpake not enough to make himſelf comprehended of any other but of his brother, to whom alone he had diſcovered all his ſecret. His wiſedome made him to judg that he muſt keep ſecret what Heaven had revealed but to him. Let us withdraw us from our little Prince, no ill things can arrive unto him, ſince God intereſts himſelf in his preſervation. We cannot divine all that which paſſed in this retreat, but it is to be preſumed, that the Abbot who had received that infant from the hands of the Divine providence, and put him into the boſom of his own ſiſter, would not neglect the breeding of it. We will leave him under ſo good and charitable a Maſter; whilſt we viſit his Mother.</p>
            <p>My Reader, I am aſſured if you look upon but the apparence and outſide of <hi>Hirlanda's</hi> fortune, that you will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it now happy: all the world indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours with complacence to content her, and no body is ſo raſh to contradict her
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170162:55"/>wil. <hi>Artus,</hi> who was the moſt concern'd in that ſhe ſhould live content, gave her every day new proofs of his affection; he was raviſhed when he could diſcover any thing which might pleaſe his wife; ſo that he gave her in this laſt uſage where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to judg, that if ſhe had been perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, he had been deceived. There was not any, even to the greateſt enemy of his repoſe, that would not perſwade her that he had paſſion to ſerve her. You com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend well that I mean <hi>Gerard,</hi> author of all the tempeſt, which the vertuous Princeſs is coming to ſuſtain. When ſhe returned unto <hi>Bretany,</hi> this young Lord was not there, that was it which gave him cauſe to diſpatch unto her a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in poſt, to aſſure her, that if ſome indiſpoſition had not conſtrained him to keep his bed, he had been himſelf the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of his joy: this evil brother in law feigned to bear a good part in the dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick rejoycement; notwithſtanding it is certain that his complement was but the pretence which he took, to make known the ſpirit of his brother, and of his ſiſter. It ſufficeth me to inſert here one of his letters, not to ſerve for ill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to hypocriſie, but to give a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caution
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170162:55"/>againſt the ſurpriſes of his malice. My Reader, you know ſufficiently the heart of <hi>Gerard;</hi> judg, I pray you, of his words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Madam, as ſoon as I had the newes of your happy return, I proteſt unto you that my ſoul, which had alwaies been ſad for your retreat, was ſeized with ſo ſudden and ſenſible a joy, that it was as hard for me to regulate it then, as it is difficult for me to expreſs it now. And really, though I had no intereſt in the contentments of my Lord the Duke, and that you were unto me a perſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, it is enough to know your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, to congratulate your proſperities. God who ſees the bottom of my heart, knowes that I have no other thought, and that as there is no man in the world that honoureth your merit more then I, there is not any one that participates more in your joy. I ſpeak this unto you, not to make you believe that I ſhould be in the rank which I have touched, but to oblige you to comprehend, that, being brother as I am, I am raviſhed as I ought. Beſides the general reaſon which obligeth all honeſt people to cheriſh the happy ſucceſs of vertue; and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170162:56"/>the particular which comes unto me from alliance, I have a proper motive to like the glory which heaven giveth unto yours. I will freely confeſs unto you, that the fear which I had leſt the indiſcretion of my zeal might have given ſome ſubject to your flight, held me in inquietude at your return, and that I apprehended, you would believe me an artificial enemy, for having endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be a faithful ſervant. My rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon repreſented to me unprofitably, that you would judg that the emotion which I expreſſed upon the accident of your lying in, was a proof that I deſired paſſionately the happy iſſue of it. I apprehended alwaies that ſome evil ſpirit would diſguiſe my carriage unto you, to the prejudice of my affection; now that you are in condition to hear from my mouth the proteſtations of my fidelity, I would, if you are the object of my imprudence, that you would be alſo the judg thereof. There is no pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment which I find not ſweet, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that my trouble might be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible with your amity; and that in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the puniſhment which you ſhall ordain me, I comfort my ſelf with the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170162:56"/>good will wherewith I deſire that you ſhould honour me. My friends will make you to ſee that there is as little artifice in my former actions, as deceit in my words, and you will acknowledg, Madam, that I cannot be ſo criminal and bold, as to approach you, after having offended you. My fever augments the ardour which preſſeth me to come to render you my devoirs. Adieu, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, I am as I have alwaies been,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your faithful humble ſervant. <hi>GERARD.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Oh traitor! If the ſervice paſs'd which thou haſt rendred to that innocent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, muſt ſerve for a model unto thoſe which ſhe is to expect from thee for the future; tell her rather that ſhe hath cauſe to make proviſion of patience to ſuffer thy malice, then to aſſure her ſelf of thy good will. As the Gentleman that <hi>Gerard</hi> ſent, returned, and had underſtood that his Maſter might come without danger to ſalute his brother and ſiſter in law, he departed from the place of his abode, and came unto their houſe; his arrivul was a new motive of joy to the Duke and Dutcheſs: he had not penetrated the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170162:57"/>deſign of <hi>Gerard,</hi> and ſhe diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled it with much wiſedom and pleaſure. There is no contentment like that to overcome a juſt anger: at the ſame time that we ſtop the ſallies thereof, we taſte the delights of a triumph. <hi>Hirlanda</hi> had the experience of theſe ſweetneſſes, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was that ſhe had not much trouble to keep her ſelf in the practice of ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable a conſtraint. <hi>Gerard</hi> failed not of his ſide to render her all the compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencies of a very diſcreet perſon, and all the ſervices of a very paſſionate friend. So that the Princeſs contributing to her errour through her proper goodneſs, and her brother by his fine policies, ſhe was not much troubled to loſe her former ſentiments, and to believe that <hi>Gerard</hi> had no leſs true affection, then he ſeemed to make ſincere proteſtations. But alas, how innocence ſometimes brings her ſelf to the diſpoſition of her ruine; and how often would ſhe be ſafe, if ſhe were a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtful! Poor <hi>Hialanda,</hi> why make you not uſe of the experience of what hath paſs'd, to ſecure you from the evil which may arrive unto you? It is not to offend the vertue of another, but to uſe ones own well; if you had a little leſs confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170162:57"/>you ſhould have much more good fortune. Why indeavour we to give ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitions and fears to our vertuous Lady? her ſweetneſs, her modeſty, her affability, and her innocence are defences good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough againſt the aſſaults of malice and of envy. Let us permit our Princeſs to enjoy, repoſe and delights, of which miſ-fortune would have deprived her ſo long time.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory obſerves that the Duke and Dutcheſs lived together in perfect intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence the ſpace of ſeven years: God never fails to do us as much good as evil in this life, to the end that this mixture may moderate our joyes, and comfort our diſpleaſures. It is not that he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to give us the recompence of our vertue, but rather a motive to hold faſt in its painful combats. His great reward attends us in heaven; in which certainly we have an illuſtrious teſtimony of the wiſedom of our Soveraign, who will not that we ſhould poſſeſs much wealth, whilſt we have need of a Gardian. In the courſe of this ſweet life, the Dutcheſs was brought to bed of a Daughter, which cauſed ſenſible joyes to her husband: notwithſtanding, <hi>Hirlanda</hi> was but half
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170162:58"/>content, becauſe he had but the moiety of his deſire. The ſum of her wiſhes was to poſſeſſe a ſon, to the end to ſuſtaine his Houſe, and to carry his name to Poſterity. But alas, how little men know that which they ſhould, they ask ſometimes children of God, and they find that they are Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers which tear out their bowels, either with their perſecution, or with their cares.</p>
            <p>Poor <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> have you not in your former. Child-bed wherewith to oblige you not to deſire a ſecond? Is it not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to loſe a ſon, without loſing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a daughter, and with her, honour and life?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gerard</hi> ſeeing that the ſucceſſion of his Brother went from him by the birth of this Heireſſe, he attempted to render the Conception thereof ſuſpected, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſpirit of his brother, as he had already done before. Notwithſtanding he would carry himſelf more cunningly then at firſt, endeavouring to cover his evil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign with ſome good pretence He go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned himſelf with ſo much artifice, that one would have thought him Protector of her whom he intended to deſtroy. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how he began to contrive his plot.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:170162:58"/>
            <p>Being one day with his Brother in a Garden belonging to the Caſtle, as he perceived that his ſpirit laboure'd with ſome melancholy, he fained to be much troubled thereat. Sir, (ſaid he unto him) I wonder to ſee you ſad in the common joy of your Houſe, and that you ſhould be the only one that participates not in the good fortune of your Family. What is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your contentments, now that heaven hath bleſſed your Marriage? Really (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed <hi>Artus</hi>) you have hit it the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and found out wherewith to comfort me; you could not better tell me, that I have a moſt juſt cauſe to afflict me, then to ſay, that I am the father of a daughter. I have a great Obligation to <hi>Hirlanda</hi> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this fair preſent that ſhe gives me to ſuſtaine ſo ſtrongly my houſe.</p>
            <p>My Reader, Judge of the goodneſſe of this ſpirit, who makes his wife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riminial for having not brought a Son into the world. Muſt ſhe not be at leaſt a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe, to content his humour? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ince the Patriark <hi>Jacob</hi> anſwered <hi>Rachel, That he was not God to give her children.</hi> I find that the plaint of our Duke is more extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant, then that of this good Lady; for if it be true, that the fathers contribute
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170162:59"/>more to the birth of their Heirs then the mothers, <hi>Artus</hi> is more culpable then <hi>Hirlanda.</hi> Behold notwithſtanding the murmur of many fantaſtick husbands, who take occaſion to perſecute, or at leaſt to frowne upon their wives, becauſe they have no children, or not ſuch as they deſire with paſſion.</p>
            <p>Our evil brother had no mind to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this to the Duke, he contented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to make an anſwer, which indeed char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged not the Princeſſe, but left her in ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion to have voluntarily contributed to this defect, through the auſterities and penitencies which weaken nature. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding (added he) we ſhould not blame a perſon, when ſhe offends but through too much zeal; otherwiſe it would be ſometimes a crime to have vertue.</p>
            <p>Behold <hi>Gerard</hi> Philoſopher and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: ſee him now Cheater and Slanderer. A while after as he perceived that his brother continued his coldneſſe, he viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his ſiſter in Law, and counſelled her to render her ſelf more complacent to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of <hi>Artus,</hi> diſcloſing unto her the cauſe of his change. It is not to be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but the honeſt careſſes of a wife can do
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170162:59"/>much upon the ſpirit of a Husband; but if he be ſavage and capricious, they provoke him more then they gain him. It is that which <hi>Gerard</hi> intended, and which he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, becauſe that the Duke being of a fierce nature, the more tenderneſs <hi>Hirlanda</hi> expreſſed to him, the more he deſpiſed her. Beſides, he began to believe that there was artifice in theſe Teſtimonies of love, and that ſhe intended rather to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, then to pacifie him.</p>
            <p>This umbrage was ſtrongly upheld by an accident which hapned one day to the Prince in the beginning of his dinner: for as he opened his napkin, he found therein a note, wherein there was but theſe words, <hi>Take heed of a flattering woman.</hi> I will not tell you who was the Author of this device; but I can aſſure you that it forwarded very much the Deſigne of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard,</hi> which was to render the Dutcheſſe ſuſpected to her Husband. Since this fatal day he ſpake not one reaſonable word to <hi>Hirlanda;</hi> when he met her, it was but to do her injury.</p>
            <p>Unfortunate Princeſſe! your diſaſter toucheth you ſenſibly, I doubt not of it; ſince it deſerves the tears of all the world, I conſent that you ſhould lament. No,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170162:60"/>no <hi>Hirlanda</hi> weep not, it is better that Vertue command with you then Impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: but if you cannot deny your tears to your griefe, I conjure you to make proviſion of them for another time.</p>
            <p>Without doubt it is not hard to judge, that our brother in Law was in too good a way to ſtop himſelf; his Artifice had too much ſucceſſe to quit the match, upon the point to gain it. His familiar ſpirit ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted him the means, which he had not yet imployed.</p>
            <p>I have not yet told you, that the Duke had in his neighbourhood a Cavalier who was redoubtable to the whole Province: the advantages which he had had in many Encounters, gave him the heart to fear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Notwithſtanding I can ſcarce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he was perfectly courageous, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he was a Traytor. <hi>Gerard</hi> thought it fit to gain this man to deſtroy his ſiſter; he tryed all that which he judged would corrupt him; but it was no hard matter to acquire a man, who was for every one that ſought an opportunity to do evil. Behold then the reſolution taken to put <hi>Artus</hi> in diſtruſt of his wife, ſee the conduct there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:170162:60"/>
            <p>After that this dangerous ſpirit had ſounded the Dukes, and found diſpoſition enough in his ſoul to receive a calumny, he took a time one day to ſpeak unto him in theſe termes.</p>
            <p>
               <q>My Lord, if I had not more paſſion for your glory then prudence to diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your injuries, I might be blamed for the il ſervice, which I am notwithſtanding obliged to render you. I would the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port which runs through the Province were falſe, it is too common to conceal it from you; if your Excellence pleaſe to give me leave to diſcover to you what I know thereof, I will avouch nothing which I will not maintain at the peril of my life. I believe, my Lord, that you are not ignorant what is ſpoken openly of the privacies of my Lady with the Lord <hi>de l'Olive.</hi> It is not but ſince to day that he ought to be ſuſpected of you, ſince all his life hath been but a continual plot to ruine her. Whilſt your Excellence was abſent, he never was from her; when ſhe was away, he kept her by one of his Aunts; now that you have begun to diſcover their practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, he flies your Court, either to avoid his puniſhment, or to diſſipate your ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitions.
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170162:61"/>I doubt not but one might ſay more thereof, if it were not better to give you only this advice by precaution, then to enlighten you too much by a truth ſo odious.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Traitor ended here, but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke more and more the curioſity of the Duke, who failed not to preſs him to inſtruct him with the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <q>It is not without conſtraint that I am to finiſh: but ſince you will have it ſo, I muſt tell you againſt my will, that no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy believes that ever you were father. Would to God that I had not ſeen thoſe privaces, which made me to know him that contributeth truely to the birth of the Dutcheſſe children. I ſhould be without doubt more diſcreet, then to ſpeak unto you of it, if I were not the moſt ardent, as the moſt obliged to ſerve you. But ſince all the world knowes this diſgrace, it would be to love your ſhame, to conceal it from him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone that can eaſily find a remedy for it. I am perſwaded that your Excellence wil approve my fidelity without my preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to a recompence for it; ſince I am reſolved to give you this teſtimony thereof, to expoſe my life to defend your
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170162:61"/>honour, and to maintaine my word both together.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Good God, what a ſtrange monſter is calumny! But what an unpitiful fury is jealouſie! How powerful is ſhe when ſhe meets with a feeble ſpirit!</p>
            <p>The firſt effect of the Impoſture of this Traytor was, that the Duke cauſed to be taken away from <hi>Hirlanda</hi> her little daughter.</p>
            <p>This Vertuous Princeſs was in her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, when a troop of Servants caſt themſelves without reſpect into her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſhe held her poor little Innocent in her armes, when the moſt inſolent of theſe Raſcals ſnatched it from her by force.</p>
            <p>My Reader, I aſſure you that <hi>Hirlanda</hi> wept not, becauſe that the violence of her grief ſeized ſo that deſolate Mother, that ſhe was rather as one dead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then as one afflicted. But ſcarce was ſhe come to the liberty of knowing her ſelf, but ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan plaints and regrets, which would have touched the ſoul of a Barbarian. But <hi>Artus</hi> had not even the heart of ſuch a one; never would he ſuffer that the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs ſhould caſt her ſelf at his feet to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore his juſtice.</p>
            <p>Poor <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> I have nothing to ſay
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170162:62"/>unto you in this extremity, which ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth my ſpirit as well as yours, if not that you muſt reſolve to dye, and to live in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence I care not to ſpeak unto you now of a Providence, which ſeems to abandon you. Suffer then at leaſt, ſince it is inevitable, ſuffer ſince it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
            <p>In the horrible confuſion which began to trouble that little Court, <hi>Artus</hi> cauſed his brother to be called, to communicate unto him his diſpleaſure, and to take his advice of what he ought to do in this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conjuncture. <hi>Gerard,</hi> who knew well that the Duke was carried enough of himſelfe unto violence, feigned at firſt to repreſſe the ſallies thereof; but it was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the end to aſſure the death of the Princeſs, and the better to cover his baſe Treachery. Perfidious, believeſt thou that all the world is blind, and that no body hath eyes good enough to penetrate into thy malice! He ſaid unto him firſt, that one ſhould do nothing raſhly in an affaire of ſuch importance; that jealouſie ought to be ſuſpected when it hath to do with the honour of a woman, whoſe moſt criminal Liberties merit death; that though the diſloyalty of the Dutcheſs ſhould be true,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170162:62"/>one ought to take heed that her puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might not be unadviſed; that his Excellence had meanes to be cleared upon this point, without putting himſelf to the hazard of condemning an Innocent; that he ſhould give this glory of not revenging an injury before ſeeing it judged. And then who would dare to aſſure that he who appeacheth the Crime, hath not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented it? Since he preſents himſelfe to the combat to maintain his depoſition, I think that one cannot juſtly refuſe her par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to produce ſome one for her defence. If ſhe be innocent, ſhe ſhould not be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, if ſhe be guilty, you need not fear that heaven will favour her malice.</p>
            <p>My Reader, you comprehend ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that <hi>Gerard</hi> would not be ſo juſt, if he believed not the ruine of his ſiſter infallible, and that if he doubted the ſucceſſe of the combat, he would not tempt the peril thereof. Moreover, he would not that he ſhould be thought to be ſullyed with the blame of a murther, which he promiſed himſelf to perform with praiſe.</p>
            <p>Great God, permit me to ask of thee, where is that Providence which watcheth over the actions of men, and glories to ſupport the Innocent? Since thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170162:63"/>our Princeſſe, and that I cannot doubt of thy equity, <hi>Hirlanda</hi> is culpable; ſo ſee I that poor Lady whom they drag to a priſon. Providence of my God! is it there that you would have her? Alas! what a great mercy would you have done her, to leave her to dye in the woods, or to live in ſervitude! her end being not ſhameful, would have been ſweet unto her, and her languiſhment ſupportable.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the Dutcheſſe expected, either the puniſhment which ſhould diſpatch her, or a miracle to ſave her, permit, after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken leave of her, that we conſider the apparel of her judgment.</p>
            <p>It is now, poor Princeſſe, that I permit you to weep; I would not that you ſhould look upon your death nor your childrens to excite your tears. Caſt only your eyes upon the ſad furniture of your chamber, call the ſervants which are by you; this ſpectacle is lamentable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to merit all your ſighs and your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grets.</p>
            <p>But what! Will they condemn <hi>Hirlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> upon the depoſition of a Traytor! Shal it not be allowed her to reproach this falſe witneſs, or to prove her innocence? O how deſirable would it have been to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170162:63"/>our vertuous Criminal, ſince ſhe could not expect any ſweetneſſe from her Husband, to live in the rigour of the Old Law, where only Adulterers dyed! If any jealous perſon ſuſpected his wife of diſloyalty, he led her to the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where the High Prieſt preſented her thoſe bitter waters, which <hi>Moſes</hi> deſcribes in the fifth Chapter of <hi>Numbers.</hi> If ſhe were guilty and had the boldneſſe to drink thereof, ſhe burſt preſently aſunder; God giving to a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle water and duſt gathered from the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, the power to putrifie her belly, and to do the ſame evil to her Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, if we believe the Rabbins. On the contrary, thoſe that were accuſed falſely, were cured of all kinds of Diſeaſes, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a Male child at the end of nine months, if their marriages had been barren until then.</p>
            <p>Poor <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> you had bitter waters enough, ſince your eyes were two living ſources of tears; but alas! they could not juſtifie you to a Barbarian, who had no ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice for you.</p>
            <p>I know not if this proof of the Jewes introduced not amongſt our Anceſtors the cuſtome of purging themſelves of the Crimes which were impoſed on them by
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170162:64"/>boiling water; a hand pure from vice came forth from thence fairer. Our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Gauls took not alwayes the pains to heat the water, but ſtripping thoſe whom they could not convict, they caſt them tyed hand and foot into a Lake or River, ſtretch'd upon a Buckler or a Croſſe; when the water bare up their body without let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it ſink, it approved their vertue. <hi>Charlemaine</hi> conſidering that a Criminal was ſometimes more light then an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, forbad that Innocence ſhould longer be ſo weighed. Perhaps he would not alſo that that glorious tree which had born Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, ſhould ſerve for puniſhment to the wicked.</p>
            <p>The moſt ordinary juſtification was made by the meanes of hot iron, which was a culter or ſhare of a Plough. One of our greateſt Kings ordained, that there ſhould be nine of them ſet in a rank, upon which they were to march bare foot without burning themſelves. The Hiſtory of <hi>Almania</hi> reports, that <hi>Cunegonda</hi> proved her Chaſtity to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond her husband in this manner; and ours ſaith, that <hi>Lewis</hi> King of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> Nephew to our <hi>Charles the Bald,</hi> deputed him thirty men, of which twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170162:64"/>ſhould make the trial of the cold and hot water, and the other ten of the burning iron.</p>
            <p>Moreover we ought not to forget in this obſervation the cuſtome of juſtifying ones ſelfe by oath upon the bodies of the Saints, Saint <hi>Denis, Germain</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin.</hi> Much more all our Antiquity reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced ſo religiouſly the perſon of <hi>Pepin the Short,</hi> that they would ſwear ſolemnly upon his cloathes, preſuming that he who had the boldneſs to approach that Royal Purple, could not be ſullied with Crime.</p>
            <p>The moſt unjuſt proof of Innocence or of Crime, was that of Duel, ſo many times forbidden, and ſo many times pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed. The firſt prohihition thereof, which was made at the Council of <hi>Valence</hi> in the reigne of <hi>Lotharius,</hi> brought ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication to the Conquerour, and privation of burial to the Conquered It is not unfit to repreſent here, the forme of theſe combats, to make knowne the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of them. When a Crime worthy of death could not be proved true, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed as falſe, the Informer preſented the Combat man to man, and the Accuſed threw downe the gage of Battle, which the Judg received after the expoſition of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170162:65"/>the Crime, ordaining impriſonment, both to the one and the other, until the day of their Duel. The time come, they were brought into a cloſe field before noone lightly, armed at the coſt of the High Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; their haire was cut round about their eares, leaving to their choice the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to annoint themſelves, to the end to be more ſupple. Four Knights guarded the field, where the Champions were no ſooner entered, holding one another by the hand, but they put themſelves on their knees with a reciprocal proteſtation, that nothing of the world but the right of their cauſe, obliged them to try the chance of Armes. After the profeſſion of their Faith, and the aſſurance which they gave not to uſe Sorcery, the Accuſed ſaid unto him, <hi>Man whom I hold, I am innocent of ſuch a Crime.</hi> To which the other anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, calling him by his name, <hi>N. Thou lyeſt.</hi> After this faire Complement, the Marſhals gave them Armes, and the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds cryed, <hi>Let them go in the Kings name.</hi> If the Accuſed remained dead on the place, he was to be hanged on a Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet; if he reſiſted until the night, he was declared Victorious.</p>
            <p>Behold the Ceremonies which were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170162:65"/>as well on foot as a horſe back: from whence it is eaſie to comprehend, God being not obliged to work miracles, that there is nothing leſſe equitable, then theſe ridiculous and fatal Duels. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that for the moſt part an unfortunate vertue is abandoned of ſuccour, it hapned often enough that an unjuſt Accuſer had better ſucceſſe then a weak Innocent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had more ſtrength and skil. And therefore I do not wonder that the Church had darted all her Thunder-bolts againſt the brutiſh cuſtomes which expoſe the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of good men to the puniſhments of the wicked; and that our Monarks, in whoſe Courts principally this madneſs was in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, have armed the Lawes to the ruine of theſe publick ruines.</p>
            <p>But alas, poor <hi>Hirlanda!</hi> Though you be innocent, you muſt either periſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out defence, or defend your ſelf without force; if your merit hath no ſupport, there will be no ſafety.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the Duke and his Miniſters im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed themſelves to ſeek out a death for our holy Princeſs, ſhe diſpoſed her ſelf to receive it Chriſtianly. It muſt be confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed nevertheleſſe, that the conformity which ſhe had to the juſt will of her God
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170162:66"/>hindred her not to complain of her evils. And to ſpeak truly, if ever a Patience hath found any cauſe to be grieved, judge you not that it is that of our unfortunate Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe! Count, I pray you, all the good moments of her fortune, ſcarce will you ſee there one day entirely happy. She enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not into her Husbands houſe, but ſhe met there a brother in Law, who made her loſe honour and repoſe. Remaines your heart inſenſible after having conſidered a woman of that condition, to wander all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in the woods, and to live in the dens; to conſerve there a life which ſhe could deſire to loſe? In your opinion is it not a ſpectacle worthy of all the pity of good ſouls to ſee a Princeſſe keep the Cowes, and to imploy her ſelfe about the ſheep? Formerly ſome Chriſtian Ladies have bean condemned to the Stable. and to the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeft Offices of a houſe; but thoſe were not their husbands that conſtrained them to live in this baſeneſſe. The Motive which cauſed their contempt, and the condition of the perſons, which ordained their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, conſolated all the bitterneſſe of their fortune. It is a pleaſure to ſuffer of the <hi>Herods</hi> and <hi>Neroes;</hi> but to have <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> for Tyrant, it is to ſpeak truly, to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170162:66"/>have wherewith to deplore. Could you not ſay that God takes pleaſure to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our innocent Princeſs? After that Cuſtome had rendred her baniſhment light, and that ſhe felt no more her evils, by reaſon of the long habitude of her fufferance, he ſent her a Cavalier to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct her into a priſon, where ſhe ſhould meet with new griefs.</p>
            <p>Let us ſeek in the life of <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> the cauſe of her diſgraces, let us ſeek in <hi>Hirlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> her ſelf: we ſhall find her life all pure, and all holy, and <hi>Hirlanda</hi> in a priſon: whilſt a thouſand perſons of her birth live in delights, ſhe languiſheth in neceſſity. All theſe conſiderations repreſenting themſelves to the ſpirit of our priſoner, it was impoſſible for her not to deplore her condition.</p>
            <p>One day the woman that ſerved her, being entred into her chamber, where for a ſumptuous couch, cloth of Eſtare, and Balliſters, there was but an old ſtraw bed, ſhe could not chuſe but ſigh. <hi>Hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa</hi> wondred at it, becauſe they had choſen her this old woman, as the cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of all the furies which they could give her; this extraordinary ſentiment obliged her to inform her ſelf of the cauſe of her
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170162:67"/>ſorrow. Madam (replied that woman) it is hard for me to command my tears, when I think of your miſeries; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, I have alwaies ſuppreſſed the grief thereof whilſt I believ'd the relief, but now that I ſee you at the point of your death, I loſe my conſtancy in loſing my hope. My Reader, permit me to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt this ſorrowful diſcourſe, to ask you what you think of the anſwer of our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs: I aſſure me that you will pardon her, if this newes put ſome little trouble into her ſoul, and if the fear of a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as ſhameful as unjuſt made her change countenance: you comprehend not well the anguiſh of her impriſonment, nor the exceſs of her ordinary griefs, if you judg that this newes afflicted her; you know not that there was no death which would not be more ſweet then her life, if you believe that the aſſurance to die, comforted her not. My good friend (ſaid ſhe unto her) I ſee well that my good fortune offendeth you, ſince you are troubled at a thing which rejoyceth me: is it not a great good to depart out of priſon, and to depart thence with aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance never to come there again? Perhaps the grave is more fearful then this priſon,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170162:67"/>I ſhould believe it, if one were ſenſible there, and that its worms were more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome then this miſery which conſumes me. But yet of what death muſt I finiſh? Madam (anſwered ſhe) they prepare the wood-pile, where you are to expire, in caſe there be no perſon that will defend your honour in taking away your accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers life. All things are already prepared, but not one of thoſe that run to this ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle, preſents himſelf to ſuccour you. She asked her further if the Lord <hi>de l'Olive</hi> were not in the country; that was the Cavalier in whom ſhe had all the remains of her confidence; and as ſhe underſtood his abſence, ſhe prayed that Governeſs to cauſe a Prieſt to come unto her to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare her ſelf unto death by the Sacraments, which are the buds of the true life, and the ſeed of immortality. She could not refuſe her that conſolation, which ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed as long as poſſibly ſhe could, becauſe ſhe paſſed the beſt part of the day with a good religious man whom they had ſent her. All the night of that fatal morning which was to ſee her martyrdome, was imployed in entertaining her ſelf with God, into whoſe hands ſhe conſigned a thouſand times her life and honour. Of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170162:68"/>all the circumſtances of her death, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing afflicted her but the examen of her honeſty, which was put over to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of arms.</p>
            <p>Never notwithſtanding did this coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Princeſs let forth one ſole tear, nor ſigh; on the contrary, imagining with her ſelf that ſhe was going to ſee again her poor children, ſhe felt a joy, whoſe tranſports ſhe was troubled to moderate: Yes, (cryed ſhe out) I ſhall ſoon ſee you, innocent victimes. But that thought gave her not pleaſure long, nor her vertue conſtancy, becauſe it made her to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that theſe two little creatures had been the innocent cauſe of her troubles and diſhonours. Then opening her eyes unto tears, and her mouth to regrets, ſhe ſpake thus to her amiable Maſter: My God, I complain not to dye unfortunate; I am grieved only to die infamous; I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand not that thou ſhould'ſt give me life, I deſire that thou would'ſt conſerve my reputation. Alas! muſt I, for being born in a great fortune, and for having poſſeſſed wealth; loſe honour? oh how much more deſirable had it been to me to be born in a country village, and to live in the incommodities of a ſtrait poverty,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170162:68"/>then to ſee me raiſed to ſerve as a butt unto evil fortune! At leaſt, my pitifull Maſter, why wouldſt thou not leave me in thoſe woods where the firſt accident of my marriage had caſt me? I ſhould have found there the trees and rocks ſenſible to my plaints, and the Ecchoes would have expreſſed my grief to ſweeten me the ſharpneſs thereof. What conſolation were it, my amiable Saviour, to live the reſt of my dayes in ſhadow and obſcurity! but it was too great a favour for a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, whom thou wouldſt render more miſerable then a country woman. Thou muſt ſee <hi>Hirlanda</hi> die in reproach, to ſee her with contentment. And well, my God, ſince thou ordain'ſt it, I conſent thereunto, proteſting, that nothing is more agreeable unto me, then that which is grievous to me: provided, that I ſuffer with thy approbation, and in thy orders, I ſhall not ſuffer againſt my will. Let us die, <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> let us die, ſince we can live no more; let us die, ſince we live but by halfes: thy poor children are no more in the world, why wouldſt thou remain there?</p>
            <p>Our generous Princeſs paſs'd almoſt the whole night in theſe ſentiments,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170162:69"/>which ſeemed to balance her ſoul between the fear, and the deſire of death: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any repugnance which ſhe had to die without juſtification, ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fented at laſt to loſe as well the eſteem of men, as her life. The break of day ſcarce appeared yet, but every one diſpoſed himſelf to this ſpectacle, the event where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of all the world feared and deſired. To ſee the conſternation of the whole town, one would have judged that <hi>Rennes.</hi> prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it ſelf for the funerals of all her inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants (this place was choſen to render the action more celebrious). There was erected a great theatre for the Court, in a place which was found then the moſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of that ſad ceremony; aſide of that was to be ſeen one leſſer, which by the apparel thereof, one would judge to be that of the poor <hi>Hirlanda.</hi> A black cloth reaching even to the ground covered it, a chair of velvet, two or three ſeats of the ſame colour made up the fatal furniture of this ſcaffold. In the midſt of the theatre was placed a table in form of an Altar, to lay there a crucifix enveloped with a cipreſs, as with a ſad cloud which preſag'd but misfortune to all the Aſſembly. The Heaven extraordinarily charg'd, ſeemed
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170162:69"/>to be willing that this execution ſhould be done in the night, ſo little light gave the Sun. There was at the foot of the ſcaffold a great number of faggots, all ready to take fire; in a word, there wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no more but the poor Dutcheſs upon the pile, to make the moſt pitiful ſpectacle that ever Hiſtory hath repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto us.</p>
            <p>My dear reader, if you have your eyes full of tears, I conjure you to dry them, to contemplate that Nobility which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared rather to be upon that great Theatre to dye, then to ſee. Behold, I pray you, that Lady which approacheth, you judg well that it is the deplorable <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> whom they lead to puniſhment; her long mourning robe; the vail which covers her face, and of all ſides deſcends even to her girdle, denotes, that it is ſhe her ſelf; at leaſt they tell me, that this equipage was that of the Adulterers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Ancients. O God! How comes it that this word is ſlip'd from my pen, ſince it hath more cruelty for the heart of my Princeſs then death it ſelf I Providence of my God, is it there then that you conduct a crowned head; which hath no other crime but its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>-fortune,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170162:70"/>and which perhaps might live in honour, if it could live in impiety? Is it ſo then that you take pleaſure to afflict thoſe that adore you? have you but racks and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments for thoſe that ſhould expect your recompences? If your thunder-bolts ſeek Criminals, behold them upon the Throne which brave your power; behold them in the Liſts, who provoke all your vengeances. <hi>Gerard</hi> and his falſe witneſs, deſerve they that you ſhould ſpare their lives? With what ſervice have they ever honoured you? Perhaps there is but the maſſacre of Lambs that pleaſeth you, and that you ſuffer willingly the Tigers and Bears to tear your faithful ſervants. My God, I will never think it, ſince thou art good, I will alwaies believe the contrary, ſince thou art juſt.</p>
            <p>Yet I ſee not any perſon that preſents himſelf for the defence of <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> and though even compaſſion of her evil ſhould raiſe her up ſome Champion, it would be only to die for company. Her atlverſary hath too much experience of his forces, to hazard himſelf in a combat, whoſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs ſhould be doubtful. This Traitor mounted a great black horſe; his Livery was of a changeable taffats, and his ſhield
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170162:70"/>bare in a ſable field a Golden Dragon arm'd and languid, which devoured a ſheep Argent, with this device, <hi>Without mercy.</hi> Seems it not unto you that all this apparel denotes the lamentable preſages of the death of our unfortunate Princeſs? Who ſees not in this dragon, and in the feeble animal which he devours, <hi>Gerard</hi> and his ſiſter in law? Let us not be ſo raſh as to accuſe heaven of hardneſs, never ſees he our miſeries without pity; but if he retards ſometimes his aſſiſtance, it is but to make us know the need thereof, and to adore the miracle.</p>
            <p>As the trumpet ſounded for the laſt time, and that every one look'd upon <hi>Hirlanda</hi>'s pile, a Champion appeared at the end of the liſts, who cleft the preſs to enter there.</p>
            <p>The Dutcheſs, who was half dead, began to be inſenſible to all kind of motions; but thoſe who had pity yet in their ſouls, conceived ſome good hope, when they ſaw that God ſent her ſuccour. Some there were that believed, that it was the Guardian Angel of the Princeſs, others would have it to be the Lord <hi>de l'Olive.</hi> All theſe names were of good Augury; but whoſoever it was, it is certain that
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170162:71"/>there was good reaſon to think that it was her Tutelar. His Courſer white as ſnow; his Livery green, ſow'd with cares of gold; his Ermine Argent in a field of Sinople; and the ſoul of his device, <hi>Nothing ſullies me,</hi> ſignified the hope of the Spectators, the cares of the Cavalier, and the innocence of the poor Lady. Notwithſtanding, there was no body that deſpaired not of the happy ſucceſs of the combat, when they ſaw a young child, who appeared to have more force in the attractions of his face, then in the nerves of his arms. His grace and his dexterity to manage his horſe, begat ſome feeble ray of confidence, but his age yet too ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, diſſipated it. My Reader, take heed that you have not the fears of that ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful aſſembly: remember that <hi>David</hi> was young and delicate, <hi>Goliah</hi> robuſtious and dreadful.</p>
            <p>As our Cavalier advanced himſelf, and had rendred his devoirs to the Duke, and to all the Nobles that accompanied him, he demanded if there was any one there ſo wicked as to accuſe the chaſt <hi>Hirlanda:</hi> Young man (ſaid his Adverſary unto him) you are ill inſtructed with the life of that woman, if you judg her ſuch. My
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170162:71"/>Reader, perinit me to diſguiſe unto you ſo the injurious anſwer that he made, I feared that you would not be touched with ſo ſenſible a diſpleaſure as our Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, who endeavoured to turn back thoſe ill words with a box, and the Lie. But he muſt imploy ruder arms; ſo the ſound of the trumpet, and the generous fury of the horſes carried them to the combat. Their firſt courſe was ſo ſtrong, that it carried the traitor half out of the ſaddle, and the young Cavalier wholly. This accident afflicted all thoſe who wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him a happy fortune, and gave occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his Adverſary to alight to pierce him with his ſword; but ſcarce was he off before he ſaw him again in his ſaddle al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as ſoon as fallen. He judged well that the time which he ſhould take to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount a horſeback, would give this young man leiſure to hurt him in expoſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his ſtroak; behold therefore rally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the ſtrength that he had, he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to fight him with equal forces, in killing his horſe. Great God, forget not that it is thou that fighteſt for inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and that thou canſt not abandon this young Prince without making it believ'd that thou wilt deſpiſe the merit
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170162:72"/>of vertue. Our <hi>Goliah</hi> having then ſtretch'd out his full arm, plunged his ſword ſo deeply into the ſhoulder of his enemies horſe, that whatſoever indeavour he uſed, he could not draw it out again. That which the wiſedome of the fleſh had ſuggeſted him to the ruine of another, ſucceeded to his own; for his Adverſary leaping off, gave him a mortal thruſt under the gorget. The joyful cry which was raiſed in the Aſſembly, made it to be comprehended that every one liv'd with the death of this Traitor: that which reſted to him of life, was but to curſe his misfortune, and to declare the Innocence of the Princeſs. <hi>Artus</hi> himſelf wept for joy of it; for though a husband be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to have lightly ſuſpected his wife of little faith, he is raviſhed to ſee himſelf deceived by the jealouſie: there is no man ſo ſtupid, that would appear juſt, by the conviction of a crime which cauſed his umbrages; in this point we love better to be judged ſuſpicious then reaſonable.</p>
            <p>Here black thoughts, here criminall diſtruſts come to acknowledg in this event, that your murmurs have raſhly aſſaulted the divine Providence; come
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170162:72"/>to render homage to thoſe ſecret conducts which are hidden to us but to be adore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to us. As ſoon as the Heralds had received the laſt word of the Traitor, they went to take the Conqueror to preſent him to the Dutcheſs. My Reader, I think that you have long deſired to know this Cavalier: you have the ſentiment of all that famous Aſſembly of our good Princeſs, who deſires with paſſion to ſpeak to him. O ſpectacle of love and joy! At the inſtant that our Champion approached the ſcaffold of the Innocent, ſhe had ſome thought that the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Ermine was a work of her hands; the ſtuffe and faſhion rather of the inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lope of an Infant, then of the Livery of a Knight, propped well her belief. Laſtly, as he put himſelf on his knees before the Dutcheſs, he declared unto her his name, his birth, and his quality: Madam, (ſaid he unto her) behold that unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſon which hath cauſed you ſo many griefs; but moſt fortunate, ſince God makes him to day Protector of her that brought him into the world. Let his goodneſs take away my life when it ſhall pleaſe him, it troubles me no more to dy, ſince you live by the means of him, who
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170162:73"/>was almoſt ſeen to be the innocent cauſe of your ruin. I know not if the poor <hi>Hirlanda</hi> believed the words of the little <hi>Bertrand,</hi> or rather, the aſſurances which love gave to her heart, of the truth of his adventures. Howſoever it was, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied not unto this diſcourſe but with tender tears, which flowed from her eyes ſo abundantly, that ſhe could ſcarce ſee him whom ſhe held embraced. Oh God! what ſweetneſs is there to taſte a pleaſure, when it comes contrary to our expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Artus,</hi> who ſaw all the careſſes of his wife, without knowing the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of them, believed at firſt that theſe demonſtrations of good will were teſtimonies of gratitude. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hee could not believe, that ſhe who had ſo many reaſons to appear modeſt and ſtaid, ſhould leave her ſelf looſe unto privacies which paſs'd the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voirs of a reaſonable acknowledgment, between perſons of different ſexes. Poor <hi>Artus,</hi> if thou knewſt thy good fortune! As the Duke was in this aſtoniſhment, <hi>Hirlanda</hi> preſented him her Champion, and ſaid unto him only theſe three words, Sir, <hi>Behold your Son.</hi> Really, I admire
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170162:73"/>not that he wanted words, ſince all great joyes are mute, as well as exceſſive griefs. When one reſents lively a paſſion, there is much trouble to expreſs it. <hi>Artus</hi> being out of his moſt deep extaſies, beheld that face which he had never ſeen, and which he believed nevertheleſs to know. All the world would have ſworn that it was the Dutcheſſes, if one and the ſame perſon could have two of them. Thoſe who penetrate a little the ſecrets of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, do know that it is the mark of a legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate birth in the children, when the ſons reſemble the mothers, and the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the fathers. Theſe are glorious ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norances to ſome perſons, ſince it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, and likewiſe dangerous to comprehend things, which may in cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the underſtanding, corrupt the heart.</p>
            <p>Whilſt that the Duke and Dutcheſs were in the examen and admiration of the wonders which paſſed before their eyes, <hi>Bertrand</hi> Abbot of St. <hi>Maloes,</hi> who had been ſpectator of the combat with the reſt of the Nobleſs, advanced himſelf to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, to inſtruct and aſſure them of a truth, which they came only to know. After he related unto them how he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170162:74"/>their child, upon the point to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away into <hi>England,</hi> he told them, that by the commandment of God he had arm'd that little Prince to defend her that was accuſed for his birth, and for his murther. He forgat not to add, that the Angel which declared unto him what heaven ordained to this young Lord, had not failed to tell him what arms he would have him uſe. And to the end that you believe my words no more then the circumſtances which render you your good fortune certain; I will give unto you an irreproachable teſtimony thereof: This ſaid, he commanded that the Nurſe ſhould be brought, whom he had cauſed to come to <hi>Rennes</hi> to put this prodigie out of doubt. The poor woman ſeeing her ſelf at the Dutcheſs feet, asked her pardon, proteſting that ſhe offended not through malice; her Highneſs might well forgive her, if the artifices of <hi>Gerard</hi> had circumvented her ſimplicity. After this confeſſion, ſhe continued to report with much cleerneſs and candour what had paſſed in the Dutcheſs child-bed, and upon what perſwaſions ſhe conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his carrying away; there need no more doubt of a thing which had ſo
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170162:74"/>many miraculous proofs to ſupport it. <hi>Artus</hi> having then ſaluted his dear wife, he held her this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Madam, I confeſſe that my ſoul is ſo divided between the admiration of that which hath paſſed, and the regret of that which hath paſſ'd between you and me, that I have no leſſe ſhame then plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſee me before your eyes. I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore with all my raviſhments the ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Providence which hath conſerved me him whom I ſuppoſed deſtroyed, and her that I would deſtroy. Let his goodneſſe for ever be praiſed of men and Angels, in that he hath vouchſafed to do ſo many miracles, to keep me from being guilty of the death of two Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents. Alas! where wouldſt thou have been, my poor ſon, if heaven had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken thee? And where would you have been, <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> if it had not powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuccoured you? But what, have I the boldneſſe to tell you that you are dear unto me, after ſuch viſible marks of cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Was it not enough that my rigour had obliged an unfortunate to flye from my houſe, without indeavouring to make an Innocent go out of the world? Madam. I cannot deny that my firſt fault
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170162:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>renders me not unworthy of your good will; but who ſhould dare alſo to doubt that you have not ſweetneſs and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe enough for both of them together? It is the only Motive of mercy which I can repreſent unto you, ſince I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in me which ſolicites you not to revenge. But if you will that I fix the hope of my pardon on any thing out of you, I conjure you by the love and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſes that we owe to this dear moie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our ſelves, to forget your miſeries and my errors, that you may live as haply for the future, as you have lived innocent for the time paſſ'd; for my part, I will contribute thereunto with all my power, aſſuring you that the only joy which I deſire in the world, is to ſee you live there content.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As he had finiſhed, and that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe aſſured him the beſt that ſhe could to forget her misfortunes, the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſt themſelves at one time about the neck of the young <hi>Bertrand,</hi> which they wet all over with the torrent of their tears. <hi>Plato</hi> hath not ill named children the glue of the husband &amp; of the wife, ſince it is true that they are not tyed to their fathers and mothers, but to unite them by that means.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170162:75"/>
               <hi>Artus</hi> and <hi>Hirlanda</hi> make the proof of this ſentiment.</p>
            <p>During the ſweet extaſies of their ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhment, <hi>Gerard</hi> touched with the remorſe of his conſcience, and convicted by the teſtimony of ſo many true depoſitions, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ſave himſelf, as he contrived the project. But whether that the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome was ſo, or that the Prince had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained it in this manner, the Ports of the Town were all ſhut, ſo that he was arreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſame place, where a little before he made account to triumph.</p>
            <p>Providence of my God, how unjuſtly do men accuſe thee, to ſay either, that thou ſeeſt not the malice of the wicked, or that thou diſſembleſt the exceſſes thereof! as if thou wert blind in thy underſtanding, or unjuſt in thy conduct. I confeſſe, that thou ſtrikeſt not the ſinner as ſoon as he merits it; but who ſees not that thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecteſt his repentance by this delay, or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditateſt his puniſhment in the mean time? O how true it is that the proſperity of the wicked melteth like ſnow, and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his fortune remaines with him, but the delicacie, which diſpoſes him to ſuffer his puniſhment with more bitterneſs. To ſee the cruelties and artifices of <hi>Gerard,</hi>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:170162:76"/>who would not have judged, that Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence could not defend it ſelf from his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution? To ſee the firſt ſucceſſes of his plots, who would have dared to hope for the vertue of his ſiſter? And yet behold <hi>Gerard</hi> in the priſon, where the poor <hi>Hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa</hi> ſhed ſo many teares; behold <hi>Hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa</hi> where <hi>Gerard</hi> promiſed himſelf ſo many delights.</p>
            <p>This wicked Prince being then convicted of all the abominable practices which we have touched, the conſent of all the world ran to a ſevere condemnation. Himſelfe thought himſelf ſo unworthy to live, that he dared not to dream of his pardon: there was none but ſhe who ought moſt to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue his death, that indeavoured to remove it. She left not out one reaſon that might be advantageous to his cauſe, but what could her goodneſs ſuggeſt unto her, which rendred not <hi>Gerard</hi> more culpable? To ſpeak in his behalf, was it not highly to publiſh that ſhe was extremely good to pray for her Perſecutour; and he exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively wicked, to have perſecuted ſo holy a Princeſſe? The more ſweetneſſe ſhe made appear, the leſſe he ſeemed to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit it; becauſe that the vertue and merit of thoſe which we offend, augmenteth much
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170162:76"/>their injury. It is cruelty to be pitiful, when the compaſſion of a Criminal makes us to forget the intereſts of an Innocent; and therefore it is ſometimes ſweetneſs to want mercy, and to bend ones reſolution againſt the favourable thoughts which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire pity.</p>
            <p>My Reader, For fear to trouble the joy which you have to ſee a Vertue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly juſtified, I will not repreſent unto you <hi>Gerard</hi> in a priſon, where both the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and the divine Juſtice have condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to languiſh all his life, his feet and hands cut off. It is true, that his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance was not long, ſince his life was ſhort. The regret to have afflicted a perſon wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all kinds of reſpects, and unto whom he owed all the love of the world, wrought upon him more then could be imagined. The laſt ſentiment which he had of his fault, made his death to be lamented even of thoſe who ſhould rejoyce thereof; as he felt himſelf neer his end, he ſent unto the Dutcheſs, to conjure her to forget his evil conduct, proteſting that he ſhould dye with contentment, if he might dye with that favour. Demand you not why I give to this Innocence the name of <hi>Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> ſince ſhe triumpheth, we ſhould not
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170162:77"/>deny her the Crown. Deſcend into the priſon of <hi>Gerard,</hi> and you ſhall ſee there our holy Princeſſe, who endeavours to comfort her Criminal; ſhe ſpares neither words nor careſſes, to make him believe, that this laſt moment of his life, razeth out the remembrance of the many years of his perſecution. To the end to take away al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſuſpition, ſhe would ſhut his eyes her ſelf, deploring his agonies, as if her dear <hi>Bertrand</hi> were dead.</p>
            <p>After having rendred teſtimonies of ſo ſweet a goodneſſe to her capital enemy, thoſe who had been but the Miniſters of his cruelty, ought not to fear any thing of <hi>Hirlanda's</hi> reſentments; ſo would ſhe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſent that they ſhould ſpeak of the death of that evil Nurſe, who left her ſelfe to be corrupted by <hi>Gerard.</hi> What (ſaid that good Princeſs unto thoſe that would incline her to that Juſtice) have you ſo little affection for me, as to deſire to ruine all the proofs of my Innocence? Know you not that it is glorious to <hi>Hirlanda</hi> to ſee thoſe to live, that imployed themſelves to make her dye? If you love me, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune me no more; I ſhould be ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, if I were perfectly juſt. So far am I from having cauſe to procure her a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170162:77"/>that I believe me obliged to give her a recompence. Hath ſhe not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied my poor little one in his miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries? Hath ſhe not preſented him the teat in his neceſſities? And not to fix me only to the ſervices which look but upon mine, am I not redevable unto her for the illuſtrious teſtimony which puts my vertue out of ſuſpition and fear? Behold how our Dutcheſſe looked upon the fault of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother through the faireſt place that ſhe could have. See how all thoſe that ſuffer like ſhe ſhould revenge themſelves with her. Whatſoever evil an enemy doth us, we ſhall alwayes have ſome Reaſon to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him, and even to like his perſecution, provided that we regard him where he is profitable unto us. But we muſt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect this diſcretion, but from Heroick Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, ſince the common ſort of men find too often darts of Offence, even in the moſt obliging favours.</p>
            <p>One ſhould not demand if thoſe who had done good to the Mother and ſon, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the reward of their ſervice and good will. The holy old man <hi>Bertrand</hi> would have no other recompence but that which he expected from heaven; but he permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his brother and ſiſter to profit by the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170162:78"/>benefits of the Duke and Dutcheſs, who conſidered them no otherwiſe then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſeeing they had been ſo long the father and mother of their dear Infant.</p>
            <p>The whole Province bare a part in the publick rejoycement; nothing was forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that might contribute to the joy of that little Court. The Turneyes, the Juſts, the Courſes at the Ring, the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Maſques, and all the other exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of Galantry, might perſwade that it was the firſt day of <hi>Artus</hi> and <hi>Hirlanda's</hi> Nuptials, if they had not ſeen the little <hi>Bertrand,</hi> who was the chaſte fruit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. After ſome years of a life, as ſweet, as the firſt of her marriage had been bitter, with a common conſent, the Duke and Dutcheſſe put their Ducal Crown upon the head of their ſon, who failed not afterward to labour with all his power the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of them both.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory hath obſerved nothing in particular of that which paſſed ſince this memorable accident; but though it ſpeaks of the good fortune of <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> we muſt not believe that her greateſt proſperity conſiſted in the petty contentments of the earth: It is in heaven that ſhe receives her full and perfect recompence; it is with
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170162:78"/>this recompence that ſhe concludes that which is worth unto Innocence, a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution which ſhe hath not merited, and that there is no vertue more deſirable, then that which poſſeſſeth nothing here below of Honours or Wealth. Who could comprehend the ſweet joyes that come unto her now from that dear ſolitude where ſhe paſſed her exile of ſeven yeares? Who could penetrate into the eſteeme of the ſuffrances of her impriſonment?</p>
            <p>Vertuous Princeſſe! There is none but you that may know the weight and value of that precious diſhonour, and of that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Infamy, which hath ſhadowed your purity, but to make the ſplendor thereof to appear with the more vigour.</p>
            <p>They hold, that the moſt illuſtrious mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument which reſts unto us of this ſtrange adventure, is in the Eſchutcheon of <hi>Breta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> where they will have the Ermine to have taken a place to conſerve honourably the memory of it. If it be ſo that the Armes of this Province have their birth in the Cradle of <hi>Bertrand,</hi> it ſeemes that they have judged very fitly, that that which had ſerved to the ſafety of one of her Princes, ſhould be employed hence-foward in the higheſt marks of their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.
<pb n="332" facs="tcp:170162:79"/>They ſay then, that after this famous event, the Ermine ſucceeds three ſheaves of corne bound with God, which <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieura</hi> with-holds in the skirt of <hi>Bretany.</hi> or rather in the Scutcheon of <hi>Gules</hi> in nine <hi>Maſcles d'or,</hi> which thoſe of the Houſe of <hi>Rohan</hi> have received ſince this divorce. I know well that ſome Authours make theſe <hi>Maſcles</hi> to come from one <hi>Maclia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> who lived in the time of our great King <hi>Lodowick.</hi> But ſurely, to diſſemble nothing my thoughts, I ſee not what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance there can be between his name and their figure. Without giving the glory of all that which we have famous in <hi>France,</hi> to Romance, we may ſay, that the Counts of <hi>Rohan,</hi> have choſen for Armes what was moſt rare within the Territory of their Dominion, where al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the ſtones and plants are traced with certain figures which repreſent <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</hi> Thus the Lords of that ancient Houſe carry Armes as natural as the Inhabitants of <hi>Tenedos,</hi> who marked an Axe in their coat, becauſe that the Crabs of their Promontory <hi>Aſterion,</hi> had their ſcale imprinted with the perfect figure of an Axe.</p>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:170162:79"/>
            <p>Though the ſheaves or Maſcles have yeilded to the Ermine, either becauſe that one of the Dukes of <hi>Bretany</hi> ſaw one day our Lady habited with that delicate and noble skin, or becauſe that the Prince of whom we ſpeak, was enveloped there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; it is without doubt that the ancient Kings of arms, who were not ſo knowing as the new, have failed in the enamel, and in the blaſon of the Scutcheon of <hi>Bretany,</hi> ſince its ground ought to be of argent, and not of ſable, but rather its ſpots which they made of argent. As much as we may call into doubt of what I write of the Ermine, at leaſt we ought not to deny that it hath alwaies been in great venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this Dutchy. I leave out many proofs thereof; without ſpeaking of the Caſtle of the Ermine, it ſufficeth me to produce only one of them, to make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that the purple was not more auguſt amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> then the Ermine was ſometimes ſo to the <hi>Bretains.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No body is ignorant, that almoſt all Soveraigns have inſtituted Orders of Knight-hood, either to witneſs to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity the eſteem which they made of the things which they uſed in their compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or to give to their ſubjects ſome
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170162:80"/>glorious motives of generoſity: ſo <hi>Charls Martel</hi> invented the Order of the <hi>Gene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> King <hi>Robert</hi> ſon of <hi>Capet,</hi> that of the Star; and Saint <hi>Lewis</hi> the ſecond of the loſs of the <hi>Genet,</hi> and of the <hi>Creſcent;</hi> leaving to <hi>Lewis</hi> the ſecond that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him that of St. <hi>Michael. Henry</hi> the third, willing to render thanks to the Holy Ghoſt for that he was born, choſen King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the year following called to the Crown of <hi>France</hi> the day of its Feſtival, he inſtituted his Order of the Holy Ghoſt: In imitation of them, the Engliſh have found out their Garter; the Burgundians their Fleece, and the Bretains the Order of the Ermine, or of the Eſpy. <hi>Francis</hi> the ſecond inſtituted it in the yeer 1450. The Coller was of two circles of gold, wherein a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Eſpies were interlaced in croſs: in the laſt circle hung on two chains of gold an Ermine paſſing upon a flowery bank with this device, <hi>To my life.</hi> I have a great inclination to believe, that the adventure of <hi>Bertrand,</hi> and the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of our <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> gave ſubject to this inſtitution. The nature of that animal, more white then ſnow, and who ſuffers rather to be taken of the Hunter, then to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170162:80"/>ſave her ſelf in a dirty place, furniſheth no little reſemblance to the purity of that Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Princeſs.</p>
            <p>I oblige no body to receive my ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but I ſhould well dare to pray ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men to caſt their eyes upon this Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. I am aſſured, if they do me the honour to ſeek divertiſement to their reading, that they will have another opinion of <hi>Hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa's</hi> miſeries on the end, then on the beginning of her adventures. My Reader, your excellent nature perſwades me that you have not ſeen this Innocent amongſt the forreſts, and in priſon, without weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with her the injuſtice of her fortune. Without doubt her little <hi>Bertrand</hi> raiſed pity in you, when you knew that he was deſtined to death; and that ſhe who ſhould give him life, carried him to the tomb. Confeſs unto me freely, have you not a little murmured in that it ſeemed the Providence of God did abandon the Innocents to the cruelty of the Guilty? Fear not to acknowledg a ſentiment wherewith the greateſt Saints have been ſometimes ſurprized; provided, that you have reſiſted an evil judgment, which ſo long a train of misfortunes hath endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to form in your ſpirit; you may
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170162:81"/>paſs for weak, but not for criminal. And though you ſhould have ſtaggered a little, I am certain that the end of this lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and marvellous Hiſtory, would have ſuſtained and redreſſed your ſteps: I dare likewiſe to promiſe me that the triumphs and glory of <hi>Hirlanda,</hi> will make you to wiſh a like fortune. Believe it not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore better then that of <hi>Joan of Arc,</hi> who would ſigh ſtill under the oppreſſion of calumny, if ſhe were not impaſſible in the glory of the bleſſed. If it happeneth that you be afflicted (without doubt it will happen) and that God recompenſeth your ſufferings in this life, praiſe his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ in that he deſcendeth ſo to your weakneſſe. If he ordains only that your vertue be acknowledged, after the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſements of envy, content you with that, and demand not inſolently where are the fruits of your merit. But if he will that your innocence be ſuſpected even unto that day of the laſt judgment, when the great Marſcarade of this life ſhal finiſh, adore with ſubmiſſion his Providence which conceals our ſanctity to aſſure the treaſure thereof. Hold for indubitable that almoſt all men paſs in the world <hi>Incognitò:</hi> thoſe that appear to have
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170162:81"/>much merit, have too often but the ſhew thereof. On the contrary, a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of perſons reſemble thoſe noble ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that traverſe our <hi>France</hi> under ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme modeſt habits: their quality is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, but their life and their purſe is aſſured. Rejoyce you at this, that your vertue is ſecret; the leſs ſplendor it ſhall have, the more conſtancy: in loſing its luſtre, it acquires merit.</p>
            <p>The ill opinion that I ought to have of my works, makes me to fear that few peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple draw fruit from them; but the good which I have of them that daign to read them, makes me to hope that they wil not be altogether unprofitable. Perhaps that the villanous ſtroaks which I give unto Calumny in my Diſcourſes, will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire the hatred thereof; and that the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories which preſent the Idea of a perfect patience, will beget the love or contempt of the perſecution of tongues. Who would be ſo weak to apprehend that little noiſe which detraction makes, or ſo inſenſible to neglect the precious merit that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth? It belongs not but unto him that thinks to loſe, to gain; when an envious perſon endeavours to raviſh his honour from him. I grant, that he takes from us
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170162:82"/>as little as may be of our luſtre, he never toucheth his true ſubject. There is this difference between the honeſt man, and the man of honour, that the firſt hath the true good, which is merit; and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond poſſeſſeth the ſplendor thereof, which conſiſteth in the eſteem. I ſhould not be of the opinion of thoſe that think that honour makes the laſt perfection of vertue, or to ſpeak better in their ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that honour is the perfect vertue. What apparence is there that the laſt fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man ſhould be out of him, and that ever he ſhould be compleated, if thoſe that look on him judg him not? Our condition would be worſe then that of the meaneſt works of Art and Nature, which receive not their accompliſhment from the thought which is formed of their excellence, but rather from an interiour term which finiſheth them. Honour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then a ſtrange mark of vertue, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny may hinder us to paſs for people of Honour, but it cannot make us not to be vertuous: in ſpight of all its envy, we ſhall be honourable, if we have merit, although we cannot be honoured, if we poſſeſs not its favour. I dare likewiſe aſſure, that detraction, which indeavours
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170162:82"/>to wound vertue, is advantageous to its glory; not only by the encreaſements that it gives to its principle, but alſo by the relief wherewith it raiſeth its rayes. They are not the beauties only of a face, which draw new graces from the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that ſeems to disfigure them: theſe ſhadowes which the malice of a jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous perſon would faſten upon merit, ſerve not but to make it to be remarkable, in the ſame manner, as there is but the Eclipſe that gives us the means to ſee the Sun. To judg at firſt, and upon the firſt ſight, one would blieve that theſe gulfs which appear in the pictures, pierce the wall that bears them, and that theſe Abyſines which a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle oyl and colours make upon the cloth, prepare ſhipwrack to the eyes and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations that contemplate them. And yet if we look here more narrowly and neerer, we ſhall find that theſe precipies are at the higheſt ſuperficies of the portrait, and that the point of the moſt eminent mountains, hath no more elevation, then the hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of theſe deep Enfonceurs; that is, an agreeable illuſion, and a profitable deceit, which abaſeth us to raiſe us; let us judg ſoundly of calumny, and we ſhall ſee, that though ſhe hath ſome other deſign, ſhe
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170162:83"/>hath notwithſtanding that effect. How many great Vertues are there which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known unto us, becauſe no body hath tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them? How many are there that glitter, becauſe malice hath caſt a cloud up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them? Not to go from my ſubject, and to leave an example which merits our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication: Should <hi>Hirlanda</hi> have come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us without her diſgraces? ſhould we have known her merit, if it had not been combatted? A thouſand Princeſſes of as high a birth as ſhe, remain buried in oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in not having met with a brother in law, or in having one better then <hi>Gerard.</hi> There is reaſon then ſometimes to wiſh misfortunes; impriſonment is then advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous; an enemy hath benefits, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, glory. But if it happen that calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny takes truly from us what we poſſeſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, never goes it ſo far as to God; the loſs which we make, will be but an Eclipſe in the Ephemerides of the time that paſſeth, and not in the book of life which remains eternally. Comfort your ſelf then, my Reader, if tongues do you ſome injuſtice: perhaps you will judg one day, that thoſe whom you make the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject now of all your hates, do merit acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thanks from your acknowledgment.
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170162:83"/>But if you cannot have theſe lights in this life, and that the love of a detractor would be a vertue too hard, I conſent that you ſhould conſerve your reputation carefully; provided, that your care be without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſment. Should you not be blind to loſe peace, which is the dear treaſure of your heart, to defend renown, which is but the inviſible picture of your vertue? In caſe that you ſhould quit a little of the tranquillity of your ſpirit, I conjure you diminiſh nothing of the Innocence of your ſoul. Remember, that that jealouſie which with too much inquietude combats honour, hazardeth not only its luſtre, but ruins alſo the merit which ſerves for foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation unto it. The fable ſaith, that <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> brake the eggs of the Eagle which he had in his boſom, in ſhaking off the mute of the bird that defiled his purple; how lively it expreſſeth that which you would do if you ſhould abandon vertue, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve its fame? It is an ill faſhion to take away the blemiſhes of a face, to ſtrip the skin off; it is that notwithſtanding which a mother doth, paſſionate of her childs complexion, and a man too amorous of his reputation: ſhe woundeth a fleſh, which ſhe would purifie from its defects,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170162:84"/>and he offends the merit which he pretends to priviledg from blame. My Reader, ſince I have but one word to ſay unto you, receive this laſt advice from me, and believe me true, if I maintain, that the leaſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome way to conſerve the eſteem of men, is to make little accompt of their ſentiment. Come you your ſelf to the practice of this generous contempt; and I am certain, that as ſoon as you leave tongues to ſpeak, your vertue triumpheth; and that if you ſuffer quietly their malice, you aſſure for ever your Innocence.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
